Mr. Malia is out of the
country. Sicker Baron Vijay Malia who
find himself in a raging 9,000 cr loan
default scam. Welcome on figuring out
sir. Why are you doing this after 9? In
India public opinion is very quickly
formed and influenced by the media
pasa loot. Hi, I'm Vijay
Malian. So it's not just huge, it is and
nothing else comes close. King Fisher is
a class apart. VJ Mallay is
you were the biggest airline in the
country. Welcome aboard King Fisher
Airlines India's biggest airline going
to be there amongst the best airlines in
the world. What went wrong? So I went to
Shri Pranabokuji then finance minister
of India. I have to downsize this aine.
I was told not to downsize King Fisher
at that time. You continue, banks will
support you. That is how it all started.
Kingfisher Airlines has been forced to
suspend all of its flights.
Kingfisher Airlines has been struggling.
At the time when you asked loan, the
company was not doing that great. Please
never forget I gave my personal
guarantee. So all this narrative of
chore people give you this kind of loan
against collateral. They took shares of
King Visha Airlines at the double
price. There's again a statement that
your international employees were
getting paid. Indian employees were not.
The company in India had no money. It
was UB's money of 260 crores. With the
bank under the control of the government
of Canada court said no. Multiple
international courts, Switzerland
authorities, one of the courts from UK,
they also found you guilty for
misrepresentation of funds.
Do you ever feel sorry that you couldn't
do anything? I apologize publicly to
everyone for the failure of King
Airlines.
Here's what pissed people off that in
your private life you were enjoying. You
had a grand birthday party, your 60th
birthday party. Do you think you
shouldn't have done that party? Why?
Somebody mentioned that you took out €35
million and invested in buying
properties in France. Rubbish. What
happened between 2012 and 2015? I made
four settlement offers to the banks
which they refused to accept. 2015 CBI
started investigating you. They found
you ciphering the money.
Third March 2016 case needs to be heard
or needs to be represented in front of
Supreme Court. Second March you left the
bank.
On 15th April, your suspension came for
your passport and 24th April was the
revocation. Why didn't you reply? I'd
like to show you something. Here is
what is the biggest challenge of doing
business in India? Government. It's in
the Indian DNA. But how did you manage
that before? Would there ever be
exchange under the table as well? I'm
not going to confirm or deny that
because I leave it to your imagination.
How do you make money now? Do you feel
restricted now? What's your biggest fear
now? Are you prepared for the
worst? Have you ever imagined yourself
actually going to
jail? Would you be willing to return to
country if you're assured fair? If I am
assured, absolutely. I will think about
it seriously. But
[Applause]
this episode is not about glorifying a
fugitive nor it is about justifying any
wrongs. It's about asking the hard
questions to the man at the center of
one of the India's most controversial
financial stories. After 9 years of
complete media silence, Vijay Malia
chose our podcast figuring out to speak
publicly for the first time. I didn't do
this podcast to celebrate him. I did it
because I was curious. I read his
tweets. I heard the headlines, but I
never heard the full side of the story
because the tweets that he makes are
different than what the headlines talk
about him. There's a mismatch. As a
podcaster, my job is to ask every
uncomfortable question, and I did. Vijay
Malia claims he never committed fraud.
He says he wanted to pay back the loans,
that his properties were seized and
sold, and that he's being framed. He
also says he's ready to face the
consequences, whatever they may be, if
he's given the fair chance of trial.
I've tried to cover his childhood,
business building, the man behind the
image, the rise, the fall, the good, the
bad, and the ugly, the life before, and
the life now. I'm not here to decide
who's right or wrong. I trust the Indian
judicial system to do that. This
conversation is for those who want to
listen, think and question. It's not
about taking sides. It's about
understanding all sides. Watch this
episode with utmost sincerity and let me
know in the comments what do you
think. Welcome on figuring out sir.
Thank you
for doing this.
And my
objective of this whole podcast is going
to be that I want to know your side of
story. There are so many things that we
have heard. There are so many things
which are probably right or wrong. I
don't know what's going on. And I think
apart from me, there are millions of
Indians who want to know the same thing.
You're highly talked about. I also feel
that there are so many things which
people have
just heard and started building their
own narrative about you. So I wanted to
out
of a in inquisitiveness, curiosity and b
out of a
responsibility I wanted to take this
forward. So thank you so much for doing
this and thank you for giving us an
opportunity. And the best thing which I
really liked about this is when you came
here and you said I'm ready to answer
everything which you want to talk
about. I don't think many people give
that opportunity. So thank you for doing
this. But the first question
is why are you doing this after 9 years?
There are thousands of people who must
have reached out to you over the years.
Why all of a sudden the need after 9
years that okay I'll say yes and yes to
us. Why?
Very good question. Nice place to start.
For the last nine years, I have been the
subject of a
vicious, relentless trial by
media in India who as you have rightly
pointed out have created so many
narratives, negative narratives about me
that I have become a lightning rod of
public
anger, being abused, called names,
And that was very
unfortunate both professionally and
personally. So rather than try and take
on this huge Indian media machine, I
just prefer to keep quiet.
Now, times have
changed and I can't help but
recalling that when President Trump was
inaugurated in the first press briefing
by the White House press secretary, she
said that a few seats were now going to
be reserved for the very first time for
people who represented new media or
social media.
I didn't even know that a podcast
existed, let alone understanding what a
podcast really
meant
until you told me and explained it to me
in a manner that I got quite excited
about because here is my
opportunity to not only answer your
questions but to say
things that I truly feel would never
ever have been truthfully reported by
the legacy media particularly in
India. That's why I'm here. Why do you
think nobody cared about hearing you
then?
In
India, it's
strange, but public opinion is very
quickly formed and
influenced by the media, more
importantly by sensationalism.
I still remember the anchor of one media
channel in
2016 shouting and screaming on the
television saying, "VJ Malia, I want to
see you in jail clothes. I want to see
you eat jail food." With an image of me
in um in jail
attire. What for? I always wondered what
for.
Subsequently, nobody bothered to step
back and think, but it was very easy to
fling false
accusations day after
day and get away with it. One of the
reasons I agreed to sit with you today
is also because it is only very recently
that finally the government of
India ministry of finance has published
a report their annual report in which
they have acknowledged 14,100 crores
recovered from me. Of course, this was
following the finance minister's
statement in
parliament
and the legacy media can't argue with
that
anymore. They can't put any spin on it
anymore.
The debt recovery tribunal gave a
judgment debt of
4,999 crores borrowed by kingfisher
airlines not by Vijay
Malia borrowed by kingfisher airlines of
which Vijay Malia was one of the
guarantors so what is the DRT judgment
debt
4,999 crores plus
1,23 crores unapplied
interest. Okay, which means notional
interest that the banks had not even
booked. Forget that the total of the
unapplied interest and the principal was
6203 crores. Okay. And I was a
guarantor. The government has recovered
14,100 crores from me. right
now if I had done
chi if I
had duped the
banks
where does this all add up till re very
recently there was absolutely no
official figure of
recovery right so everybody the legacy
media in particular wrote whatever they
Ed
right and I was in no position to
contradict
today after the government of India has
acknowledged the recovery of 14,100
crores I think it's my turn to ask them
what they have to say about it because
you say that a lot of things about you
are false narrative let's go down to
from your childhood we speak from the
beginning and you tell me everything
that people have been said people think
it's wrong and I'll try to present the
facts and the narratives which I have
heard and which I have gathered through
my research. All right. And if you're
okay with counter somewhere, I'll
counter you as well. No, please, please
feel free to counter me. If there's
something that you feel is debatable or
you want to make a counterpoint, I'm
ready for it. Perfect. because I feel
that's my little responsibility out
there to to hear the right side and the
wrong side both and let then people
think about it and let them make the
right call. That's fair. Perfect.
So before even I ask you about childhood
do you do you regret anything?
I regret one
thing which is that after all my hard
work, all the value that I created in so
many multiple
ways that effectively the government of
India and of course the
media made me a zero from a
hero and that's a fact of life that I
have had to stomach and live with. Now
whether that was justified or not is
something that I'm sure will be
encompassed in your own
questions. Zero from a
hero. Let's talk about building of a
hero first and we'll come down to zero
again. So before the billionaire Vijay
Malia, before the controversy, before
all of this flamboyance and scandals and
things that people talk about, who was
Vijay Malia as a child? Where were you
born? What did you do? How was your
childhood? Tell me about it. Born in
Kolkata, moved to a hometown
Bangalore. Went back to Kolkata. did my
schooling there, did my college
education there in
Kolkata and my upbringing under my
father was a very
normal I would say strict upbringing
really. Yes. Tell me an incident strict
childhood. Two things. When I was still
in
school, class nine at La Martineer in
Kolkata, my marks were not very good in
class. I was a
mid-ranker only because I took a lot of
interest in sport and extracurricular
activities. I didn't I you know
concentrate fully on studies and my mark
sheets.
And he told me and I think most people
know it. He was exceptionally
intelligent. Uh was a product of the
Dune School. I think topped his class.
So he expected me to also top my
class.
Uh nevertheless he said something to me
which I think I remember till
today. Two things made a profound
impact.
one, if you're not good
enough, you are not going to step into
my shoes.
And the second thing he
said, he said, "Do you
realize that while I say step into my
shoes, there may not be any shoes at all
because the government and its then
socialist
policies may have taken everything away
from us and the only thing I can leave
to you is your education. So take it
seriously." I think I repaid some amount
of faith because
um for my last three years in school 9
10 11 I think I came within the top
three in class and he was quite happy
about that.
So weren't you a little spoiled as child
spoiled? Oh my god. I was anything but
spoiled really. You had all the fancy
toys. You had all the things that
Absolutely no fancy toys at all. That's
completely false
narrative. I after I passed out of
school and when I went to San Javier's
college to study BCOM, my father was
very clear, you go to college at 6:00 in
the morning and when you finish at
10:30, you go and work a full day at the
office as a management trainee. I was
put on a stipend of 400 rupees a month
and that 400 rupees never increased
right the
way my time through college. So that's
all I got 400 rupees a month and was
working in those days fips and company
limited old courthouse street in
Kolkata every day after college. Aren't
there stories that you used to go to
college in a very fancy car and you
removed the silencer just to show the
the noise of your car, the loudness of
your car and you were always a show off,
weren't you? I was no showoff at all.
And the fancy car that I have was a
secondhand standard herald. So where are
these stories coming from? I don't know.
People's narratives, people's
perceptions. That's why it's important
to correct those
perceptions. You know, talking about
noise, even a fat fat in Delhi makes a
hell of a lot of
noise. You don't have to drive a fancy
car to make a noise down the street.
So, you are telling me that all these
stories of you having a you having fancy
toys, remote control cars, and then
fancy cars with loud noises, all of this
is false. Well, I may have tempered with
the silencer of my car. Okay. Uh because
I was always into kind of fast cars,
loved motor racing and stuff like that,
but you know, I mean, it still remained
a standard held. But why did you do
that? Like just to show off like the
noise and everything. Look, if you can
modify the silencer of a car like you
can modify the the top end of a car's
engine to make it go a little quicker. I
mean that's some that's the basics of of
motorsport. But how were you as a child
like personalitywise? Were you
confident? Were you a little arrogant?
No. No. I look the this is all a
question of
perception.
Uh arrogant is also your understanding
of arrogance. My understanding of
arrogance. But I'll tell you one thing.
H
I was always
self-confident and whenever I was
invited to give talks at various
universities and educational
establishments I always told the
youngsters that when they start off life
they must be
self-confidence because it is only
self-confidence that will bring out the
best in you and I still believe that
till today and because I started
young I am passionate about youth
empowerment but this would have not been
the case always as a kid we all have
like lot of insecurities it's not always
confidence what was your biggest
insecurity when you were growing up I
don't yeah probably the biggest inse
insecurity was when u the examination
results with you and what my dad would
have to say about
But no beyond that uh you know my life
is pretty plain and simple um great
bunch of school friends, great bunch of
college buddies
um in
Kolkata. uh not the glitzy lights of
Bombay and yeah so it was pretty normal
but you know nothing fancy but I had a
very strict set of supervisors at work
who were clearly instructed by my father
to be tough with me to make sure you
know I worked my butt off and I'm none
the happier for it that's what made me
but did you did you ever get to a
position or in a thinking as a child
that one day I'll be powerful, one day
I'll be very rich? No, absolutely not. I
mean, how could I be so presumptuous?
Here I had a dad who was hands-on
working 24/7
uh
young uh and and uh who told me that if
I didn't measure up, I'd have no place
in the business. So I couldn't be
presumptive could I? But your father was
a wealthy man. In those times there were
only few wealthy people. So you would
pres presume this right? Like I will
have all this wealth inherited. I'll be
maybe bigger than my father or maybe
just have all of these things. I didn't
have any such aspirations in those days.
Uh and and you know wealth was something
that was very relative. Um and and my
father certainly was a very frugal
spender. So uh irrespective of how much
wealth he had, he certainly wasn't
expensive.
You said when you used to go to work,
your father put strict supervisors. Mhm.
Right. What would those strict
supervisors made made you do? What?
Well, first of all, make sure that I
came to the office on time, straight
after college. It wasn't as if I'd sort
of roll up whenever I wanted to. Okay.
The second I was given a clear set of
tasks. Um I was a salesman. I had to go
and visit the shops in the market. I had
to visit
distributors. Um I had to uh spend time
with the accounts department to
understand accounting, corporate
accounting. Um yeah, and marketing, you
know, sit with the ad agencies and stuff
like that. So it was a comprehensive
training program but with no forgiveness
in any sense. I had to work a full day.
I couldn't sort of get up and go uh or
come when I
liked which was fine. I mean um looking
back it was a great grounding.
What happened next? So you were in
Xavier's you started going to work and
then you went to states. Yeah my dad
sent me off to the states to work for
American H. Okay. American Herx as it
was then known became then
Aventus and now the pharmaceutical
company the global companies called
Sanopi. So yeah I was sent there uh
worked there once again um as a
management traininee. I then was brought
to England to work in Jensen and
Nicholson. I was a paint foreman in the
paint factory. used to be mixing paint
at
night and yeah I mean slowly I
understood what my father's methods were
what were his method which is basically
a
strict training
regimen and I did pretty well because I
can tell you he he expressed he
expressed
um his his appreciation for my work. I
got a a pretty good uh report card from
America. He was he said he was proud of
me. Um I did well here in England mixing
paint and um when I went back to India
um his health was becoming indifferent
even though he at that time he was only
57 years old. His health was becoming
indifferent. he had a history of heart
disease. So he sort of got me to work uh
for him in the core
business and
um yeah then of course the story of
Kingfisher the story of McDonald's
number one backpiper and all these
brands that subsequently became very
wellnown began then. How was your
relationship with your father? The
relationship with my father was
excellent. He was a man of few
words. Uh but there's one thing he did
which embarrassed me no end. That every
time he saw me, he gave me a big kiss on
my cheek. Whether it was at an airport
or in the office or at home, he'd give
me a hug and a big kiss on the
cheek. I mean bless him for that. Was he
did he ever doubt you that you will be
able whether you will be able to
continue and build his legacy or not? I
think the biggest certificate I got was
from my bosses in America and they gave
me a pretty good certificate a pretty
good report and that finally I think
gave him the confidence to say ah my son
is stepping up to my expectations.
What was your first bold step in your
father's company?
Oh, King Fisher. I went to my father and
I said, "I need 10 lakhs rupees to
market Kingfisher beer." He said,
"That's a princely sum of money. What
are you going to do with it? How are you
going to do it? Etc., etc." Because I
saw in the archives of United Breweries
this label of King Fusha Beer, which had
been actually launched in
1857, okay? gathering dust and you know
with a pretty archaic kingfisher bird on
it sort of prehistoric
version but I said to myself the the
mere word brand
kingfisher is very evocative in so many
ways it could be made into a fun brand.
Now my time in Kolkata going back to my
training days when I spent time with
them with the marketing department more
importantly interacted with the people
in the advertising agencies. my time in
America where
um you know I still
remember the two big banks which is Bank
of America and City Banks and City Bank
said the city never sleeps and Bank of
America came out saying we caught the
city napping you know that was the level
of marketing advertising tongue-in-cheek
stuff which caught your attention and so
I became fascinated with marketing
And I came away back to India started
working in the business and I always
said a brand needs a
personality. Of
course I very quickly realized in India
I couldn't replicate what they did in
America because for alcohol India is a
media dark environment where the
the advertising of alcohol is banned.
So in a way I had to think of ways of
authoring surrogate advertising
uh which I did pretty
successfully you know not some Mickey
Mouse
stuff where if you want to advertise an
alcoholic brand that you sort of
suddenly you know produce some music
cassettes and I built a full water
business around
Kingfisher and a bought a business of
sign significant enough size
uh that you could justify advertising
it. Okay. And therefore you you
advertise the core brand.
So I gave King Fisher a very colorful
personality
because that's what evokes
you
know like Magdal number
one golden moments Magdal
moments it's evocative it's supposed to
convey that you know if you want to hang
out and have a good time with your
friend golden moments well it's the
Macdonald moment. So there were many
many such
examples of how I actually gave brands
their
personalities
and in many ways I supplemented by
becoming the brand ambassador
myself and all of this was happening
when your father was still alive. Oh
absolutely absolutely.
You said India was media dark when it
comes to alcohol which still is the
reality and there was a point where I
think government banned alcohol. No, no,
no, no. Or what was that? Certain states
introduced prohibition
such as Andhra Pradesh, unified Andhra
Pradesh.
Of course, Gujarat has always been dry.
But the advertise advertising of alcohol
is banned in India and has been banned
and still is banned. When was that? When
was this time when you started acquiring
a lot of alcohol brands?
uh because a lot of those brands were
scared of the state because the state
were was getting involved in the alcohol
business or maybe they wanted to ban or
prohibit certain things. What was this
time where you started acquiring certain
alcohol brands and cheap because you and
your father was bullish on it.
No, that was in 1977 when Majaraji Desai
was the prime minister of India and he
publicly announced that there should be
prohibition all India. Okay. Okay. which
means that alcohol should be banned
across the country. So obviously the
stocks the value of the stocks and
shares of almost all alcoholic beverage
companies whether distilleries or
breweries fell. M my father was very
clear that prohibition could never
succeed in India and
therefore he
bought and so that's how we became
number one by quite a fair
distance because all those who panicked
and sold
out my father acquired.
But was there something you guys knew
which others didn't or it was just pure
conviction? No, it was just pure
conviction because we knew that uh
prohibition had not even succeeded in
the United States. And plus, if you look
at the amount of revenue
generation for the state governments
through the sale of alcohol, there's no
way in the world that prohibition would
have succeeded in India. What h what
happened after your father's death? You
were doing this successful stint. You
were taking bold steps. You wanted to
make alcohol a cool brand. All of this
is happening. Everything was going
right.
Right. What happened then? Well, um I
was in I was in the US. I gone to
finalize promotion and export of Black
Dog Scotch whiskey.
uh when my father sadly passed away at a
cocktail party in in then
Bombay
and he was only
59. Uh nobody ever expected him to pass
so young. I was just past
27. So I took the air and death flight
and flew back from New
York and performed my father's last
rights.
Then the fun began
because my father surrounded himself
with a few
stalwarts. Yeah. Meaning people who he
put in positions of great
authority who were also very close to
him personally.
So he
had somebody running the western India
businesses, somebody running the eastern
India
businesses, somebody running the
southern India
businesses. And don't ever forget in
those days the structure was that United
Breweries Limited was the the holding
company and the other companies in the
group were largely
controlled by its largest shareholder
United Breweries or they were subsidiary
companies. And so the inevitable debate
started on what
next, what role I should have. Of
course, people acknowledged that I was
in the business.
Uh
but people I think were a little
reticent to speak openly about
uh their own aspirations of being the
chairman. Then something very funny
happened. We had uh annual general
meeting of shareholders that
uh was coming due. Mhm.
And the shareholders in the front line
who had seen me with my
dad proposed my
name and that's
how all other aspirants were
silenced because they couldn't publicly
sort of get up and say that they were
more
qualified particularly when it was
evident I had shareholder support. M and
there I was. I was installed in what I
call the hot seat at a very young age.
But fortunately, thanks to my
upbringing, my father's
insistence on proper training,
familiarization with the business, time
in
America, time working with him. I wasn't
raw. I had a fair amount under my belt
to be able to address the challenge of
the role. I was reading an article where
u it said that you didn't trust people
who was who were in control at the time
of your father's uh when your father was
a chairman. So that's why you hired your
people and your friends because you
didn't know that if you could actually
go to them for the right advice or no.
No, no, no. That's completely
misleading. It's false. I never hired
any of my friends. But let's put it this
way. They would have been too young and
inexperienced. In any case, you know, I
mean, as I said, I was barely 28. They
would be my contemporaries. M so the
question of hiring them and putting them
in management positions just didn't
arise but I encouraged a lot of
professional from within I mean people
who then became the president of the
spirits division of the breweries
division and all the rest of it I mean
my father's time the average age of the
regional directors of the regional
satrups was probably around 60 between
60 and 65 and in In five years after I
reorganized, I mean the average age was
about 40. Okay. And these were all
professional managers promoted from
within the ranks.
I mean yes there were couple of
exceptions where I hired people from
extremely well-known organizations
uh like major consultancy firms so on so
forth but beyond that largely it was all
internal promotion.
compare or give me differences
between
before okay so when your father was the
chairman versus when you were the
chairman give me three four differences
what happened in United briefies
it was the entire approach for instance
mine was a
decentralized accountability approach
okay
uh I would have
monthly operating review meetings called
MS for each line of business. Okay.
And that's all I wanted to know about
how the businesses were performing on a
regular day-to-day basis. I wasn't
leaning over the shoulders of the
management team and trying to
micromanage
things. Um when opportunities came
along,
uh then of course we'd had separate
discussions. So if you empower
people, accountability comes along with
it because people are
also motivated to demonstrate their own
capabilities. Now my father's style was
as I said far more hands-on owner
operated micromanaging management style
and he spent a lot of time doing it. Um
I had a lot of free
time. Um as I will tell you as we
proceed because because of this
decentralization and this whole new
management culture Mhm. that I had
enough time in your um introduced in in
the UB
group and this was between let's say
1983 and
87 that is why I was able to
then acquire the Burgger paints global
business based here in the UK and
actually become a non-resident Indian
in ' 86 88 8 Okay Yeah. And I still have
a letter from the Reserve Bank of India
confirming that from 1988 I would be
treated as a non-resident Indian
uh for tax and exchange control
purposes. And the reason I and of course
that obviously meant that I couldn't
spend more than 180 days in India. Mhm.
Well, the luxury of spending 180 days
out of India running this new
opportunity in international business
means business. Uh I was able to do it
only because of the decentralized
management structure implemented in
India. So
both the foreign businesses and the
Indian businesses ran very well.
Give me differences and similarities
between Vital Malia and Vijay Malia.
Well, Vital Malia's
thought 100 times about spending money.
Vijay Malia probably thought
twice.
Um yeah, you know, I guess it's age. Um
it's aspiration, its age,
it's
different styles and outlook on life.
Was there any difference in terms
of public attention as well? You were
pretty loud. Your personality was I No,
look, once again, you can think whatever
you want to think of me and so can the
whole world.
Just because I'm a self-confident guy
who is not afraid of public
speaking who doesn't suffer from stage
fright. If you want to say that I am
arrogant,
flamboyant, go ahead and say it. I can't
deny it. My father was very shy of
public
speaking. Totally the opposite. I am a
very confident public speaker. I used to
debate in school. I used to participate
in drama in
school.
So I can speak.
So you didn't want public recognition.
You loved speaking. No. Well, if
somebody asked me a question or I was
invited to speak, I'd speak and people
would well in some cases tell me I'm
talking nonsense and in most cases say
they liked my speak. But I was able to
communicate from a platform.
But won't you speak certain things and
tweak your speeches in a way that that
becomes headlines?
I never looked for headlines. I never
ever looked for headlines.
The headlines were created around me by
the
media. You know, let's take the case of
flamboyance.
Okay? And let's spend a minute on
analyzing flamboyance.
To me, flamboyance
means loving
life and appreciating the good things in
life. That's what flamboyance is.
In a public way. Okay.
That is what I would say is the meaning
of
lambards. How old was I when my father
died?
28. Compare me to other industrialists
in India at that time. I was 28. I was
chairman of UB group. Who was chairman
of RPG enterprises? Mr. Ra
Prasad. Who was the chairman of
Reliance?
Dhubayani. who was the uh chairman of
the Brila group Mr. BK
Bella I was a contemporary of their
children
but I was thrown into the deep end. So I
was a group chairman being compared to
people who were my father's age.
Now as a
youngster I had the the passions of
young people like I
enjoyed a good
car. I
enjoyed my
drinks. I enjoyed parties. I enjoyed
music. I enjoyed sport.
Not all of my father's contemporaries
who suddenly became my contemporaries in
business lived that way. They were more
conservative, you know, more at home,
more domestic, consistent with their own
age. So suddenly the media decided, huh,
this guy, chairman of UB group, is
flamboyant. I was flam termed flamboyant
only because I did what every other
youngster aspired to do.
You know, I mean, at the end of the
day, you have to make
allowances, age related allowances.
Let's put it that
way. But it's okay. I have no regrets. I
I didn't I didn't spend anybody else's
money. I spent my own money. I lived my
life the way I wanted to live my life.
Uh if I look back, I've got millions of
miles of
corporate experience under my belt
starting off at a very young
age and um I hope people appreciate the
more positive contributions that I have
made rather than the persistently
negative narrative that has overtaken
and overshadowed
a effectively a whole career. I don't
think I ever use that word
flamboy. It was the media and the
narrative they created around me that
was
flamboyant for their own purposes.
Now I just lived like any
other moderately wealthy 28 year old
would live. No. Yeah. extraordinary
life. How can it be extraordinary? In
what way? Do you know what the exchange
controls were in India? Do you know if
you could import a Ferrari in India?
Today you can. But go back to the
198586. Could you import a Ferrari? No
way in the world. So did you or did you
not? You could only buy cars from the
state trading
corporation through an auction process
in Delhi.
But you ended up buying all of them. I
could
not. later you bought it. Look, I like
good cars. I race cars. I've been racing
cars since I was a
teenager. Okay, I brought a Formula 1
car into India to race. Okay, when my
father was still alive. In fact, when I
won the race at
Scholabaram, okay, near then Madras, now
Chennai, I called him from the racetrack
and said, "I won the race." He was very
happy. So it wasn't as if I was trying
to do things behind people's back. But
okay, I was fond of motorsports back
then.
Okay. So it came from media. But did you
enjoy the tag of your Where did I have
the time to enjoy or spend my time and
energy denying? I just lived my life,
did my work. And I think whoever you may
ask I work really hard. See this is
very okay this is very like a media
answer. Okay. U what did you were aware
that people call you Flip Point. You
were aware that this was the image built
being built. You were aware that
headline. What was your reaction? What
did you start secretly? Did you enjoy
it? No way. So what was the reaction the
moment people would write it you like
ignore it? Of course I would ignore it.
What have I done for the last 9 years?
But at that time you peak you let me
tell you something
being referred to as flamboyant some
people may take as a compliment but
nobody will
tolerate being called chore,
thief,
fugitive. Right? These are damning
words. I ignored all of it because I
knew I couldn't fight it much like I
ignored
flamboyance. I couldn't spend all my
time devoted to contradicting what the
media
wrote. Yeah. And now but okay let me
also tell you I referred to earlier I
said you know this
whole theme of
flamboyance the media if you'd see the
pattern of their reportage on me okay I
mean and they kept on writing things
which really I thought these guys don't
have anything better to do vija party
vijay mala is hosting Newest party at
King Fishella Vij Malia is doing this
that and other things. Okay. Bottom line
is they
created a narrative of a
personality that helped them to sell
their own media. One day there was a
terribly wrong factually incorrect
uh article in one of the large
newspapers in India. So I called the
owner. Yes.
How could you
possibly publish something like this
without checking the facts?
Vijay, sorry. Your name
sells. So they created this animal
called Vijay Malia whose name started
selling so they could they could they
could they could you know get more
eyeballs, more readership, more
viewership. But be that as it may, I
lived my life. What was my
objectives? I am not apologetic for the
life I
lived because I didn't spend anybody
else's money except my own.
I didn't borrow one rupee from
anybody. Okay?
I
was much
maligned, much
complimented, but effectively I was my
own brand
ambassador. Take the case of
one muchtalked about phrase, king of
good times. Yeah.
I'm not
crazy to walk around with a label on my
chest saying king of good
times read. And this is where somebody
must make the
effort. See the label of the king vishab
beia that was
developed. It says the king of good
times. The personality of King Fisher
Bear was the king of good times. Ulta
media started calling me the king of
good
times. So tell me being the king of good
times will not help sell the beer. But
it did the because the beer itself was
the genuine king of good
times. And the personality that I gave
King Fisher, promoting sport, promoting
fashion, promoting
music, sponsoring motor racing. So all
the stuff that's exciting to
youngsters that represented the
personality of the King Fisher
brand. That's why King
Fisher was such a success. But talk to
me about building of King Fisher. Don't
you think it was a like at least that's
what I think it was a very well curated
strategy that I will become a brand
which represents King Fisher. No, I was
brand
ambassador and I have done it not only
for King Fisher but take the case of our
spirits business. I actually came on
national television with an ad
encouraging
people not to drink and
drive. I did it myself. I didn't get
some film star to do
it. I did it myself. So bu becoming a
personal brand was a strategy then. Of
course it was. So then why does it
bother you that you wouldn't bother me
act as like the king of bothered me? But
that's what I'm saying. But I am not the
person who labeled myself as king of
good times. You happened that the media
started calling me the king of good
times. Fine because subtly you c curated
this. No, I didn't curate king of good
times. In what way? By actually
promoting a lifestyle which every young
person would aspire to. Why not? People
young people are entitled to
aspirations. M young people are
entitled to improve lifestyles. Young
people are entitled to to treat
themselves.
Um yeah, but that doesn't mean I went
around the whole world saying, "Well,
you know what? I'm the king of good
times." No way. Never said it even once.
But you knew it will happen. No, I
didn't. How should I care? I achieved my
objective of making King the number one
selling beer. That's it. How did that
happen? What happened along the way is
is irrelevant. Okay. How did this
happen? King Fisher beer. How did it
become number one? Tell me story of King
Fisher. Well, when I took over this
business, Golden Eagle or Mo Breweries
was the largest beer company in India.
Today, United Breweries Limited controls
almost 52% of the beer market in India.
King Fisher is is I mean not very many
product categories that can can
lay claim to 52% market national market
share but yeah Kingfisher is by far the
number one selling brand that's because
yes I cured a personality around
Kingfisher around fun around excitement
around vibrancy color I created the
brand and I achieved my objective you
take the case of of of Mcdal number one.
I mean once again this whole golden
moments, Mcdal moments, right? Uh it was
a little more sober than the Kingfisher
ads because the target demographic was
different but it's the largest selling
whiskey in the world today.
Number one,
right? All these brands I created.
Tell me one turning point which just
made everything good for you in King
Fisher. Kingfisher beer specifically.
It's a sustained effort. But what was
when was the first time you thought okay
now it'll work because it was always
working it as the from day one. Yeah.
When I relaunched it new packaging,
right? Make it more appealing on the
shelf.
uh started sponsoring music, fashion,
events, got more brand
attention. Automatically the sales
started picking up and then you know as
we went along promoting our marketing
strategy which was clearly effective,
the sales
followed. Same thing with with Macdonald
number one whiskey. Nothing is
overnight.
National brands are not built overnight.
There wasn't one moment that you could
point pinpoint or was it? How can you
how can you pinpoint a moment because it
isn't like switching on and off a light
switch. Why did you get conviction that
King Bishop beer will work because it
was little expensive than other ones.
We had brands such as UB
Royal, Flying Horse, we had Jubilee. Now
you tell me even though they were my
brands, does any one of these evoke any
excitement in you? No. But if I say to
you King Fisher, I mean you take notice,
right? So that's the platform I built
on. All right. Similarly, I said I mean
you take the case of of Macdonald number
one, right? It was
uh targeted at uh slightly higher
demographic, but it went along with more
sophisticated
um uh merchandising and stuff like that
which which which ordered well for the
brand. And today as the Indian economy
has grown as consumer spending power has
gone up it's the world's biggest
brand selling about 32 million cases per
year. What was the biggest challenge in
building of King Fisher
bec I think or everything was just
painted red and it worked out for you.
No no there was nothing red about
Macdonald. It was all black and gold. Uh
the only one around that's red is King
Fisher. No, I think more than
challenges I look at opportunities. I
mean you know 2005 I bought Shawless my
biggest competitor. I mean that
propelled the spirits business I mean to
number one position by far brought on
board banks like Royal Challenge and all
the rest of it. So I mean those were
pretty bold business decisions which
once again self-confidence. I had to pay
$300 million for the company. Big amount
of money but made it work. That's how
United Spirits was created today with a
market cap of almost one lakh crores. So
you know I mean she had the confidence
to do it. You go do it. You said you
bought Bojo paints at the same time.
talk about that. Why paints all of a
sudden you were making money with
alcohol? You were minting profits out of
alcohol. You were convinced that brands
like King Fisher and then at one point
other brands as well would work out
really well, which it did. Why
buying a paint business like this is so
the paint British paints in
India. Okay. which is now called Burgger
Paintants
was part of the Hex Group. My father was
chairman of British Paints India. Okay.
When he passed away, I became chairman
of British Paints
India. During my tenure as chairman of
British Paints India, I learned
something about the paint business.
Right. Now,
what did you learn about paint business?
Go back in time what I told
you. When I was
sent to America, then to England, I
worked as a foreman in the Ber Jensen
Nicholson paint factory here in this
country.
So I not only knew
about making paint but also how a paint
business was run because I was chairman
of
budgets. So when Hex Group decided to
sell their global budget pens,
headquartered in England, operating in
the Caribbean, operating
in
Africa, in uh Asia, the true
multinational company.
Uh I went to them and put together a
um loan package with those days the Hong
Kong and Shanghai Banking
Corporation and bought it because I had
this aspiration of creating India's
first
multinational that was back yeah I said
1988. Okay. So from being a
Indiancentric business I was operating
in 25 countries worldwide flying the
Indian
flag. So your objective is only that I
want to take India or Indian business to
the world. No absolutely not. I I I I
was was
uh very focused on making a hefty profit
out of it too. All right. Uh which I
successfully did. So I bought it in a
leverage buyout. Mhm.
And after that I did
IPOs. I did IPOs in Jamaica. I did IPOs
on the Kenyan Stock Exchange. I did an
IPO on the Singapore Stock
Exchange and diluted our shareholding to
51%. But used the proceeds of the IPO to
pay down the
debt, right? And then finally in 1996, I
sold the entire business that was then
listed on the Singapore Stock
Exchange and I made a fat
profit. And I still remember and I have
no hesitation in saying this that I went
to my mom and I said, "You see this
piece of paper? This is what I
earned. This is not
inherited. I made it
myself. So when I spend it, don't
complain." And that's on a lighter end.
Yeah, I mean I I I that was when as a
non-resident Indian I made my first
serious piece of money out of entirely
my own
initiative in a pence
environment. But hey, that's is what
it's all about. I mean I got experience
of doing IPOs in three different
countries across the globe. That was in
invaluable experience. Do you regret
selling it? Because today BGER is I
think 60 70,000 cr big business. That's
only one BGER in India. I own the global
BGER all over the world including India.
I sold Bger paints in India to dingas.
So do you regret selling? A great job
with it. No, God bless them. They did a
super job with it. But it was if it was
doing so good, why did you sell it then?
Well, uh, it was bought by the
Malaysians.
Okay. And they came with an offer I
couldn't refuse. I mean, okay. They
offered me some two and a half times the
quoted shapers.
Okay. You mentioned that you said you
told your mother that I made this
profit. Now don't complain when I spend
it. Correct. Tell me about relationship
with your mother. My mom brought me up.
I used to live with her in Kolkata alone
since ' 64
65 and yeah so she's stood by me like a
rock she's a very well educated lady
um and yeah I mean she's been living in
England now for 30 plus
years
but yeah I mean you know I mean I wanted
to buy a
yacht I wanted to buy a plane and stuff
like like that. And so I wanted to make
sure I set the record straight. I told
my mom I earned this money. So if I
spend it buying a yacht and spend it
buying a plane, don't complain. Did she
complain? Oh, no. Never. But why did you
say that? She enjoyed the art. What?
Okay. Why did you say this to her then?
Was she like frugal? She would ask you
not to spend. No, it isn't that. I mean
it's natural for a parent you know if
you see something that's quite
extraordinary quite expensive lavish
call it what you may it's normal
parental reaction to ask the child you
know why you spending money or whatever
so I mean I'm just telling you I made a
joke out of it but I was very proud that
that was money I earned you know it
wasn't money I inherited it. Tell me one
lesson you learned from your mom.
Oh, I've learned many
lessons from my
mom. Don't waste time and life arguing.
It's not worth it.
Use your time productively. Think
positively.
Don't keep arguing with people unless
it's a matter that's going to get you
somewhere. And which argument gets you
anywhere. And what did you learn from
your father? Give me one lesson.
Something that you can't forget.
Hard work and an ability to read a
balance sheet. Company balance sheet.
He was really good at it. Right. That's
what it's written about him. Super
little at it. Do you miss your I don't
think I'd be I'd be as good but I think
whatever I learned from him was good
enough for me to produce some excellent
robust balance sheets in all the
companies I ran. Do you miss him? Well,
who doesn't miss a dad? But you know
it's now what 1983 to 2025 is a long
time.
What do you miss about him? You can't
keep missing somebody for 40
years. Life is too short for that. But
do you think he would have been proud of
you today? Well, I would hope
so. Certainly not proud of me being
called chore or
and certainly nobody would be proud of
that. Certainly no parent. I know my
mother gets very agitated even today.
She's 98 years old and every time she
sees the Indian media, she's reduced to
tears. Obviously, it hurts her more. I'm
probably more thick skinned, more robust
and I just ignore it. But, you know, at
that age, my mother doesn't and it's
very unfair what has been written, what
has been alleged because it's complete
nonsense. Let's walk through the case.
Let's start from the point of what
happened in Kingfisher Airlines. Okay.
When did you decide that you want to
start a kingfisher a
2002 2003
and you just Okay. So here's a story.
Hear me out. What I've gathered from
reading about it
is one day out of blue you go to an AGM
or like just a board meeting I think not
AGM it was a board meeting where you
announced that on my son's birthday we
are going to launch Kingfisher Airlines
your CFO was not happy about it but you
still pursued and you want to do it this
was the this is what is reported
What was the reality? Tell me the truth.
The truth is that Damana brothers from
Bombay. Mhm.
Who previously had Damana Airlines M
came and made a presentation to my
CFO Ravin
Aruni saying the time is ripe to start
an airline now.
Okay. Ravender had discussions with
them came to me and said would you like
to look at this proposal? I said
yes. We looked at
it and finally we decided yes it is
opportune so let's go for it. Okay.
That's how the idea of an airline was
bomb
and then you didn't take anyone in
confidence. You were just hey out of
nowhere I think we are alcohol business
now we want an airline business.
No there's nothing wrong in
diversification. The UB group has had a
history even during my father's time of
operating food processing companies.
petrochemical companies,
electromechanical companies. So I mean
diversity was nothing new to us. So your
initial plan to launch an airline was
7th May 2005 but you ended up launching
on 9th May 2005 right and then this
whole business of launch on son's
birthday as a birthday gift and all is
complete baloney. All
right. I think my son would be
embarrassed and I would be equally
embarrassed to say I'm starting an
airline. All right. As an 18th birthday
gift. Complete nonsense. All right. But
okay. Once again, media narratives are
best ignored.
A fullblown professional management team
was in position before the airline even
started before the first plane arrived.
Okay. The CEO and the director of
engineering were both hired from the US.
Okay. And the airline was launched.
There's a lot of narrative about
Kingfish
Airlines. There's a lot of narrative
about mismanagement.
A lot of narrative about the Dean
acquisition. All sorts of things. Let's
pick one by one. What was the first
vision of King Visher Airlines when you
were starting in 2005? To produce the
best flying experience that India had
ever seen.
Make it a premium experience. totally a
premium experience number one terms of
passenger comfort, safety, number two to
connect places in India that had never
ever been connected before and that it
was a really serious part of the growing
infrastructural needs of the country.
Hm. But I was watching one documentary
about you
and I think the person who you got to
lead was Alex. Yeah. Will Cox. Yeah. So
Alex said
that you convinced him that you want to
build a lowc cost carrier but it was not
like that. And in your own words, if
you're giving a vision that I want to
build a premium experience, why did you
get a CEO or like a president, I don't
know what was his position, but somebody
to lead by telling him
that you want to build a lowc cost
carrier. That is your own
misinformation.
He said it somewhere. I'm not I'm just
quoting him. Fair enough. I haven't seen
it, but I'll respond.
Kingfisher Airlines started off as a
singleass airline, low
cost but with a
difference. It had inflight
entertainment and it offered meals.
Everything else that's applicable to a
lowcost airline was applied to King
Fisher as well. commonality of fleet,
commonality of training, the whole lot.
I mean there's a whole set of rules.
What is a lowcost carrier? What is a
full service carrier? Right? And that
even descends down to intricacies such
as the type of reservation system,
flight planning system you use and all
the rest of it. So Kingfisher had all
the lowcost attributes. Okay. The only
product plus was inflight entertainment
for the first time ever in India and
good
food. So to me the logic from my
marketing experience was Indians love
entertainment therefore the inflight
entertainment system and Indians love
food. M so good food right and then of
course okay service quality whether
whether you're a low cost or a full
service I mean you'd like a nice well
trained polite set of crew and we spent
a lot of time and energy on
that
then when we saw the market
evolve we added king fisher first which
is basically the business
class.
Why? Because the market demanded that on
certain
routes, right? There's certain people
who would not fly King Fisher because we
didn't have a front cabin or a business
class who would always fly jet. Okay?
Because Jet had two class, business
class and economy class, right?
And now just to prove my
point, Indigo is often referred to as
the most successful lowcost carrier in
the world and certainly the largest lowc
cost carrier in India. What's Indigo
doing now? Installing a business class.
Right.
Yeah. So it's not such a dumb idea.
So it worked in your favor initially.
Yes. So by and by 2008 you were the
biggest airline in the country having a
27% market share. Yes. Right. What went
wrong?
If things were right, your marketing was
working, you had everything right. In
fact before even you answer that I want
to go to which is often talked about is
your training of cabin crew. What was
the idea behind that? you selected
certain people based on how they look or
how they're going to be presented. Yeah.
Well, you know, I mean, at the end of
the day, you have you have very
good-looking ladies
who sadly can't speak very
well. Now, what is one of the key
attributes of a cabin crew?
Communication.
I mean you may look
good but if you can't communicate with
the
passenger that doesn't serve the purpose
the kind of service standards that I set
for the airline and my service standards
were unique they included in business
class
the
aeroses cleaning the reading glasses and
spectacles of our customers. We call
them
guests,
right? So there were little things that
made a vast difference in the customer
experience. Tell me two more thing. Two,
two, three more things. This is one.
Okay. Secondly, the food was second to
none.
Right. I mean the quality of the seats
themselves, the recline and all the rest
of it, what they call the seat pitch,
it's second to none. So there was so
many little attributes. We
called
customers not passengers but guests.
Many airlines have copied us since but
they were the little little things that
made a difference. I was very focused on
the service delivery excellence of King
Krishna. You can go further because you
don't know this. You can't ask me the
question. So let me tell you. Yeah. In
the first one
year, the airport manager at every
single airport in India had to send me
on my personal mobile and
SMS the flight
number, the schedule time of departure
and the actual departure time.
So every night before I went to bed
which was rather late I used to look at
my phone every single flight of King
Fisher of that day I used to monitor
personally the on-time performance. You
were so detailed focused. You were so
because the the service industry in the
airline industry
requires focus requires detailed focus.
So agreed then it worked in your favor
till 2008. What happened then? Simple.
You ever heard of Lemon Brothers? Yeah.
You ever heard of the global financial
crisis,
right? Did it not impact India?
Of course it did. The whole aviation
sector was forget aviation. Every sector
every sector was. Yeah. The money
stopped. It got dry. The value of the
Indian rupee. So I went to Shri Pranab
Mukhuji then finance minister of
India having grown up in Kolkata. I
speak fairly decent Bengali and I
said I'm a
problem king Airlines downsize
which
means I have to downsize this
a cut number of aircraft. I have to lay
off employees. M right because I can't
afford to operate under these depressed
economic
circumstances. He said
no at this time connectivity is
important. Yeah. The jobs and employment
are important particularly because you
know typically in an airline they're not
blue collar workers. Huh? M these are
not like work men. Yeah. And the the
boys and girls who work in an
airline can't be classified as blue
collar. And he said I don't want them to
lose their
jobs. So you continue banks will support
you. That is how it all started.
I was told not to downsize King Fisher
at that
time and yes the banks did support. All
right. Now
what happened then? Lot of well you tell
me the narrative. I'll tell you the
truth. You tell me the narrative. Then
there was a consortium formed of 17
banks and the loan was given to you via
SBI right? Was that the first or IDBI
was first?
See this is where people are not aware.
I acquired Eden
which everybody says was a big mistake.
Yeah. What? In $137 million or something
like that.
Everybody says you overpaid for it. In
the world of
business, there's something known as
consolidation, industry
consolidation. There is something known
as eliminate the disruptor. Okay.
Eden was famous for advertising and
promoting one rupee tickets. Yeah.
Clearly you could never ever
sustain any airline business selling
tickets for one
rupee. Right. Okay. It was a bait. H
but that
set certain price expectations in the
mindset of the customers. Yeah.
and affected not only Decker which was
losing money but the industry as a whole
of which King Fisher was also a part.
Right?
So at that time we looked at
it was also Bangalore based. It had the
same Airbus aircraft. It had the same
train pilots as King Fisher. So there
was a lot of
engineering compatibility
plus scale and
size with a merger of Kingfisher and
Deka eliminate the
disruptor and consolidate the industry
and Kingfisher Airlines. That was the
logic of buying
Dean, not
this much
touted logic of I was desperate to fly
overseas. I needed to get past that
5-year hurdle. Complete nonsense. Now,
why should I shout from the rooftops
trying to trying to clarify this? But if
you talk to anybody about elimination of
a disruptor and consolidation of
industry, it'll start make and
commonality of equipment, it'll start
making business sense. But if your
philosophy was to make a premium
airline, why would you buy something
which stands for lowc cost carrier,
which stands for something cheap, which
stands for one rupee ticket? Because the
customers would be completely different.
The only obvious sense which anybody
could make it out from it was if you are
going for a different vision you are
probably going out because the 5year
window which you wanted uh which you
wanted to bounce right probably yeah of
course like that was the logic like I to
clarify to tell people who don't know
about it the logic that people talk
about is if an Indian airline wanted to
fly overseas they should have operated
in India for at least 5 years before
getting the license to operate air and
you didn't have that and that's why you
bought air deck in so that you could
start flying overseas and you paid an
absurd amount of price for it that's
what people say so who is the people
that you're quoting everybody like all
the things that I've read all the all
the media like media right yeah like the
legacy media right the legacy media the
people who are responsible for giving us
the information I mean that's what as a
citizen that's where I get my
information from correct and at least
from the ones who I really respect. So I
don't think anybody at UB group was that
dumb with a lack of business
understanding to buy an
airline, an operating airline just to be
able to fly overseas.
I'm telling you the logic
was consolidation of the
industry given the commonality of
equipment.
I referred a little
earlier to the installation of a front
cabin or business class which we called
king first which Indigo are doing even
now. There are certain routes in India
that demand
right a front cabin where there are
people who will only fly business class
fair but the bulk of
India people want a single class
product Dean fitted that bill
fantastically
right we opened up more routes than had
ever been opened before or available for
air connectivity
That was one of the biggest
contributions we made to the Indian
aviation sector and economy.
Right. Dean also played a part in
that.
So, Kingfisher's sad failure
subsequently had nothing to do with
Dean. Okay. Nothing to do with how much
we paid for
Dean. Right. Got it. Those were totally
separate set of reasons.
Right. But business reasons. Here's a
question on it. So I get the idea that
you wanted to service more routes. You
wanted to consolidate. That was a
business decision. You saw that hey I
want to build a premium airline but
there's a bulk of India who cares about
the price and you wanted to contribute
to make sure that I want to make sure
that India gets to fly anywhere and
everywhere through the price point which
air deckin provides and if I could be
the one to consolidate it and I could be
the one to actually eliminate the
disruptor I should do it. Business
decision brilliant. Do you think then
the wrong decision was to rebrand it to
King Fisher Red? Because you can't start
operating one Deckan and one King
Fisher. So we just called it King Fisher
Red. I mean rebranding is is is common
in the world. Take
Coca-Cola, right? There's Coke, there's
Coke Zero, there's Diet Coke. It's all
Coke, right? So a multibrand strategy is
no rocket science. Yeah. But then the
philosophy of air decken was low cost
and in kingfisher red. So kingfisher
stood for premium. Kingfisher red stood
for low cost. It was differentiated king
fisher
first and king fisher red. Okay. Right.
You tell me something. What's the
difference between coke zero and dad
coke? Tell me. Just two names I don't
know. Yeah fine. What's the philosophy
behind it? You don't know. So how can
all these commentators be commenting on
king pusher first and king pusher
red? You know the the trouble in India
is that there are too many commentators
who don't understand the facts and of
course the media plays to the
gallery and that's how
disinformation gets spread
wide and
then you stated somewhere again the
commentators I'm quoting that I want
to if I've put in a name king fisher on
an airline no matter even if it's low
cost I want to provide all the services
you started providing all the services
you started providing catering you
started providing everything in a lowc
cost carrier didn't you I began by
saying that king fisher started off with
all the attributes of a lowc cost
carrier which is single class
standard fleet etc etc etc but I said
the only differentiator was inflight
entertainment and food
[Music]
I mean just because I gave food didn't
make it a full service carrier. I mean
you want shall I give you examples?
Yeah. You go on any lowc cost carrier
here in Europe. All right. Do they
starve you or do they feed you? But you
have to pay for it. No. All of them. I
don't know. A few of them. The ones I
Okay. So there are exceptions. Okay.
But that was the business like that's
what everybody talks about, right? You
know that's the problem. Lack of
information and knowledge and more
importantly no domain knowledge of the
aviation industry leads to all sorts of
speculation that makes no sense. So you
tell us
that does it make business sense to
provide food and inflight entertainment
in a lowc cost carrier where people
don't care about it. Wait, our belief
was Indians love food and love
entertainment.
That was for King Fisher first, but not
for Kingfisher Red. King Fisher Red
stands for low. An inflight
entertainment system doesn't cost you
money to operate every day
but still cost you a lot of money which
eventually will bleed your balance
sheet. Really? I'm asking you.
Not in our opinion. Do you think that
was the wrong decision? What? which is
provided. Yeah. After acquiring deck
giving all the services of a full full
service
carrier in a lowc cost
carrier the flow the the full service
carrier part of it was very distinct
from the so-called lowcost carrier. Uh
at the end of the day, however you may
refer to these business models. Mhm. Uh
it's all about the
price your customers are willing to pay
and whether you can fill your plans.
Simple. So all models are
academic and
theoretical that really are irrelevant.
But your critiques say
that you were competing against other
lowc cost carriers like like at that
time was it I think Indigo started at
that time and Spice started at that
time. I think Spice Spice was there on
and off. Yeah. But more often than not,
so you were competing with lowc cost
carriers with their pricing, but you
were providing something extra and
that's why your business model was
bleeding more money than them and you
expected that this will turn into loyal
customers. But the moment you increase
price, people would not fly your CL your
flights. Was it was it true? That's what
the critics say. They are all aviation
experts. I have nothing to say.
So where was the problem then? If this
was not the problem, then what happened?
The problem was the
government. The problem was fairly and
squarely the government. And I, you
know, they've made a lot of political
hay out of this. When I used to write to
Prime Minister Manm Singh,
uh when I used to write uh to to to the
civil aviation
ministers, ministers of
finance, the cost of crude,
international crude went to $140 a
barrel.
The price of aviation turbine fuel in
India was directly related to the cost
of international crude
oil. So you can see that from an average
of about $60 a
barrel, crude oil went to
$140 a
barrel with the resultant and equivalent
increase in the price of aviation
turbine fuel. M the state governments
levied and ad valorum sales tax on
aviation turbine fuel. So you can
yourself now begin to imagine the
financial impact on the
airline operating where fuel costs are
the single largest component of cost. So
I
pleaded I said look please give aviation
termine fuel declared good status so
that it attracts central sales tax and
not this punitive
advalorum state sales tax right because
the states are making windfall profits
anyway that the government did not do
okay aviation
is regarded as a capital intensive
industry,
right? It's acknowledged as such
worldwide,
right? They would not permit foreign
investment. It was sad that only 6
months after King Airlines shut, right,
that they permitted Ajiad to invest in
jet. I had already reached agreement
with the CEO of Edihad in Geneva for
them to invest in King Fisher which
government did not permit. So we could
not capitalize the airline through a
foreign investor either. Why didn't they
allow? They should ask government.
Right?
So my point
is the economy, the
circumstances, the government policy
then
existing all conspired to create a
perfect storm through which King Fisher
could not survive. I mean that's a sad
part of it. If you talk about Kingfisher
the
concept and UB group's diversification
into aviation, I'll answer it in one
sentence. The two biggest orders for
aircraft in the world today are Air
India and Indigo, both Indian
carriers. The fastest growing aviation
market in the world today is India.
Now if you yourself acknowledge that in
2008 Kingfisher was the largest airline
with a 27% market share. Had
events not conspired against
us.
Right? You can imagine where King Fer
could potentially have been today.
But sadly not all businesses work out.
Sometimes you win, sometimes you lose.
While this like 2008 turmoil happened
and you had your own challenges with
King Fisher, but there were good things
in your life which are happening as
well. Mhm. One of them being
sports. So you you bought IPL team RCB
Royal Challenges Bangalore. How did that
happen? When did this idea come to you?
Were you approached? You approached what
was it? Tell me everything about it.
Well, I think I've already explained to
you the concept behind building a
personality for a brand. Mhm. About
communicating
um marketing
u
ethos via sporting events, via music
events
um and various other forms that would be
attractive to youngsters.
I had just acquired Shawless and one of
the biggest brands that I acquired was
Royal Challenge
Whiskey and I was thinking of ways and
means of now taking Royal Challenge
whiskey to the next level which required
a lot of marketing
innovation
thinking and at the time the IPL was
conceived I was actually sitting on the
um BCCI committee as a representative of
the Karnataka State Cricket
Association and I was very impressed
with the pitch that Lalit Modi made to
the BCCI committee about this league.
Mhm. And of
course uh he was working through
um jumping through the hoops. BCCI was
quite bureaucratic at that time. But
nevertheless, he called me one day and
said, "Okay, fine. We're ready to go.
Teams are going to be auctioned. Are you
going to buy?" And I thought to myself,
I said, "Wow, in a country where cricket
is a
religion, what better platform can I
have to promote my brands than through
an IPL franchise?"
And I got greedy. I wanted one for King
Fisher. M and one for Royal Challenge,
my whiskey brand. Okay. He said, "No,
you cannot possibly have
two. You can only have
one." Anyway, bidding time
came
and I think I was pretty excited about
having an IPL team to promote one of my
brands.
And so I bid for three franchises. Okay.
I lost Mumbai by a very small amount of
money. But then that's not surprising
that Aman's got it. But anyway, I wound
up being the highest bidder for three
and I had to choose one. So I obviously
chose
Bangalore and it then was natural that
it would be Royal Challengers Bangalore
because the whiskey was Royal Challenge
and that's how RCB was born. But it was
not a business it was not for the love
of cricket. It was more like a business
decision that it will help my brands or
was it both? This is it. The media
narrative will
be well vanity project. Vijay Mala loves
cricket. He wanted to buy his own team.
Yeah.
Flamboyance. The usual narrative about
me. But the sole purpose always was
promotion of the Royal Challenge whiskey
brand. So it was very much
businessdriven and that's why it was
called Royal Challengers. But did it
help after that? The whiskey sales went
up massively.
massively and of course quite apart from
it doing its job to promote the whiskey
brand the IPL franchise model itself as
explained in great detail by Lalith
um and which is true now is that the
revenues the media revenues is so high
the payment of the franchise fee over 10
years is over so now there's a
significant net profit for every
franchisee It's like a very profitable
running independent business. So, so
much so for it being a vanity project.
How much did you buy it for? I think
$112 million is what I bid. And that
time it would be like 6 700 crores or
more than Yeah, I think but but Lit was
clever. He everything was denominated in
dollars. The bid price was okay. I think
112 million which of course people boked
at at that time but you know in
hindsight if you look at it and do the
math it was a top class investment. I
mean look at what the teams are worth
today. Yeah. I mean there was a billion
dollars. You know one thing which was
exciting in your pitch in your bid for
RCB was Virat Kohli. Virat Kohli under
19 you bid for him and you if I'm not
wrong you got it for like 20 lakh
something correct why did you pick Virat
at such a young age well you know
obviously there was the young
creditors and it was draw by lots
right and finally I got lucky so I got
to pick and I immediately went for Vart
you know, I mean, I looked just I
think shortly before the actual um
selection
process there, they were playing the
under9 World Cup and I was very
impressed and so I picked him and you
know it's wonderful 18 years later he's
still there. They were just his
performance or were you going to see
something? Yeah, he was a young kid at
that time when I got him. But you know,
full of energy, great
talent and you know, one of the greatest
Indian cricketers ever. If you had the
choice to pick two or three players from
other teams for RCB today, who would you
pick? If dreams could come
true, just brea.
Yeah. if dreams
could come
true. Uh Surya Kumar
Yadav Visha
Pant Rahul if I had these
four I wouldn't need anybody else and
definitely win the trophy.
And do you think this year even when you
don't have these four you would the RCB
line trophy this year the RCB lineup is
pretty balanced
um top class batting lineup
uh a much improved bowling lineup
um I haven't seen Bhuvar Kumar play in
RCB colors yet but you know he's a top
class bowler
um but as a unit I can say it's a pretty
balanced unit and now it all depends on
onfield performance. You know this year
the captain Rajat he's from my city he's
from my neighborhood. Oh like like he
was literally like two houses away from
my house Rajat Partidar. So this year
even though I'm not I support Mumbai but
this year I'm still voting for RCB and
I'm like okay let let Rajett win the
trophy.
Okay. But it you know it occurs to me
that RCB never winning the cup has
actually worked in the RCB favor. Do you
think so? In what way? In cult
following. No. Even though you guys have
like the RCB has never won. You see that
is because the day
RCB was conceived
we have had a comprehensive program of
fan engagement.
Okay. Right. We've had event I mean the
the the IPL window is 2 months but we
have had activation program stretching
over all 12 months. Keep the RCB fans
engaged. So it is once again a a
three-cut marketing strategy and fan
engagement strategy which has worked.
That's why we have such extreme loyalty
that win or lose the chant of RCB is
always there. Give me an example of the
marketing trick here. So many I mean you
you watch the activations of RCB
longevity right? You
remember LA?
Yeah. Remember? Yeah.
Lao. When was this conceived?
You don't know. Well, let me tell you.
1996 World Cup of crickets. The
Kingfisher West Indies cricket team. Now
back in
1996 I put the Kingfisher logo on the
West Indies not Indian cricket team.
Okay. And because why? The personalities
of the West Indian
cricketers fun dancing music their
entire swagger that suited the
Kingfisher brand. That was when the
jingle was conceived which lives on till
today.
It's
2025. Yeah. Wow. It was conceived before
I was born and I still remember
it. So you see you have been king of
marketing. You have done so many
marketing cakes, right? Was the Formula
1 also a marketing stint for King
Fisher? See, I told you earlier that
I've always had racing in my blood. I've
always loved racing cars.
I was then involved with the motorsports
clubs in India. I was chairman of the
federation of motorsports clubs of India
uh for many years and the job of the
federation was basically to promote
motorsports in India. Now for anybody
who is into motor racing the absolute
pinnacle of motorsport in the world is
Formula 1.
right now. What is Formula 1 all around?
The image of Formula 1, big box,
glamour,
uh, seriously competitive racing divided
by hundreds of a second, full of
excitement, etc., etc., etc. All the
attributes I have employed in different
ways for my
brands and plus being a motor racing
enthusiast, right?
It was a
dream to have a team on the F1 grid. So
when the opportunity presented itself, I
did
it right. I did
it. Now I named it Force India. I could
have easily named it Malaya Formula 1
like Williams Formula 1 for instance,
right? But why did you keep Force One?
because I wanted the Indian flag to be
on the
grid. I wanted the world to know that
the team with roots in India of all
countries was at the pinnacle of
motorsport and that is why I called it
force India and I had the triricolor on
the
car. Of course I also use the platform
to advertise my brands. Yeah. Okay.
including Royal Challenge Whiskey, White
and Mai which we owned at that time,
King Fisher, then the airline. So the
car, deliver the delivery of the car and
all the merchandise around Formula 1 had
a lot of our brands on it for
promotional purposes. But the core
reason was to put an Indian Formula 1
team on the grid. But you invested quite
a money quite a lot of money on it,
right? Sure, I did. I mean, Formula 1's
not cheap. Do you think that was bad
decision? No. In hindsight, I wouldn't
do anything different. Why not? Because
why not? Because you had to sell it,
right? And I think a lot of accusations
are for the same brand. Whose
accusations about what? That you use
King Fisher money for Formula 1 and
nobody talks about it. Nobody talks
about that.
Have you spoken about it before and
still people do? I've never Why should
I? As I told you, I don't want to waste
my time
correcting the barrage of narratives
coming from Legacy Media.
But then you sold Force One. Yes. Force
One became Racing Point. Yes. You sold
it to Lawrence. Aston Martin Formula 1.
Yeah. Why did you sell it to Lawrence?
Well, I had to at that time because of
my worldwide freezing orders and the
troubles that Sahara was going through
and so on and so forth. So you know at
the end of the day I would have
definitely kept it but it was not to be.
So fine you you move on in life but I
had 10 years of the Indian flag on the
Formula 1
grid. Talking about another marketing
stint because there was cricket, there
was Formula 1, there was Kingfisher
calendar. It was so highly talked about.
What was the story behind Kingfisher
calendar? Atul Kazbaker came to me and
said fine let's you know there's a
Pirelli calendar um why can't we create
a similar property for kingfisher
absolutely and so we said fine we'll
have the kingfisher swimsuit calendar
uh we couldn't go sort of kind of all
the way that Felli might have been able
to given the social considerations in
India and so on so forth but I think um
we we we we produced a product that
everybody demanded. I mean even today I
get SMSes from people where's my
calendar. Um so it was highly sought
after
uh and once again we we had events
around it. We had the national uh hunt
for the king fisher girl and that was
national. So we broad-based it and we
chose models through a national hunt and
then of course we'd have events
uh around the calendar shooting the
calendar and then launching the calendar
all of which was consistent with the
brand positioning and marketing strategy
of Kingfisher.
And why do you think
that girls who were who became or who
landed on the calendar their career
skyrocketed? Well, because we chose the
right girls. I mean whether it was
Deepika Pardon, whether it was Katrina
KF, I mean we we had all the the the
heroins and the the
uh the
stars uh on the calendar in their
younger days. But they were not stars
back then. They became after. We picked
Well, we picked the right talent. Did
you also help them after the calendar or
it was just the engagement was only? I
came with the calendar and that was it.
I did it because it was a fantastic
marketing
tool. Didn't bring anything to me
personally, but it did wonders for the
brand. The same thing with the Mcdal
marketing campaigns. Right. Okay.
Talking about fast cars, I've always
been passionate about cars, right?
And I have owned good cars, but not a
fleet of them. In
India, I had a couple of Mercedes cars,
one Rolls-Royce, and one Mayback. That
was it. That was all I possessed. But
you have one of the largest car
collections of vintage cars and stuff,
right? We're talking we're talking
talking about vintage cars, which is a
totally different ball
game because of
our nationwide presence on the
ground. I
told my
people, "Look for vintage
cars because they were hugely neglected.
Many many cars went to India in the 20s
and 30s. The Maharajas in India were
probably the biggest
customers for famous cars such as
Rolls-Royce. But these cars were in a
state of ruin. Given my inherent
interest in
cars, I said I want to collect these and
restore them, which I did. I mean in
those
days I have bought a Rolls-Royce for
50,000
rupees with a tree growing through it in
somebody's
backyard deep in
Talangalana. I have bought cars that
have been rusted, parts missing, etc.,
etc., etc., all of which I lovingly
restored over a period of time. That is
my passion for cars and those cars still
exist. Of course you you can't export
them because that's a government of
India policy. So they are in India.
Tell me tell me about the top three cars
which you absolutely loved out of your
collection from the vintage cars back
then which you owned maybe in England or
in India or anywhere. Yeah. No, in in in
India, I had uh I think a 1931 PS arrow,
which is a fantastic American car
uh and which I took to
Singapore. I entered a Singapore to
Malaysia rally and won it and very
proudly flew back on an Air India flight
with a big trophy in my hand. That was
one of my favorite cars. I um have a
Rolls-Royce Silver Ghost that was
supposedly owned by the Nisam of
Hyderabad with a very unique body on it.
Uh that's a special
car. I um have I think a 1903
Darak which looks more like a horsedrawn
garage. It's French with a single
cylinder engine still runs. So yeah,
these were some of the unique ones which
u were personal favorites. Let's put it
that way. What's the most ridiculously
expensive thing you have bought in your
life? It depends what I
mean. You're talking about a car, you're
talking about painting, you're talking
about property.
Give me example of one each.
No, I mean
look uh I have a family trust set up by
my father that you know uh has acquired
various properties in different parts of
the
world. The media said I had over 20
properties probably one in each country
I went to which is once again hugely
erroneous
exaggeration. Yeah, sure. I have
properties in England, properties in
America where my kids live. I had a
lovely property in France, which you
rightly pointed out
uh owned through Gizmo, which is a
holding
company. Uh yeah. And then when I had uh
the big brewery business in South
Africa, we had a home in Cape Town which
was sold when the business was sold
because I had no reason to keep going
there. That's about it. And you talk
about one of your houses which was very
spoken about actually two of them. Yeah.
One is that big bungalow which is above
which is in India at the King Fisher
Tower. Bangalore Bangalore. started it
started off as a joke. Okay. What story
behind it? The brewery
house which is the bungalow was on that
piece of land for over 100
years. That's where I grew up in that
bungalow. That's where my father lived.
And so when these developers came
and asked me that that land should be
developed and that it would be very
beneficial for the
company and that there was a huge profit
potential. I said, you know, I should
put the company
first and unlock the value and the
potential rather than be
uh selfish and say no, I'm not
moving. So in a joking way, I said to
Van
Razak of prestige, very dear friend of
mine, top man. I said
by if you lift this building and put it
on top of the tower you want to build
I'll agree. He says okay that's what
we'll deliver that's what they did.
Wow. What what is there in inside the
house? I always wonder every time I go
to Bangalore. It's unfinished. It's
unfinished because it's embroiled in
this UBL liquidation controversy right
now. But you know given that the the
banks are settled and I think UBHL
should come out of liquidation and be
restored to its shareholders which is
what I'm working on
now. Was this also a reason why because
you marketed so well and you marketed at
the place or with the tools which were
very very public in nature very loud in
nature. There was a line which I read in
a newspaper which said you were a show
you are a showman and your father was a
businessman. Is that is that why people
misunderstand you because of the nature
of your My father was a
businessman and I
really am not concerned about being
referred to as a
showman because the showman created the
world's largest alcoholic beverage
company which my father as a businessman
would have loved to see.
Do you think your
father if he was here with you things
would have been different for you? You
would not land in this? Absolutely not.
Absolutely not. I mean if you
see what I've been
through, it's
illogical. It is a sustained campaign
and a sustained attack on the
government's favorite poster boy.
Right now whether my dad was around or
not would not change anything what has
been attempted and what has been done
till
now the
government officially recognizing and
admitting that 14,100 crores has been
recovered. Okay. Let's go to a point
where when we were talking about earlier
about the kingfisher turmoil you said
you went to the FM back then. Mhm. which
was Pranav Mukharji
sir. What happened after that meeting?
He said that banks will support you. Is
that the reason why a government bank
supported you? It was not one government
bank. It was a group of about 15 or 16
government banks. Kingfisher Airlines
never borrowed any money from State Bank
of India. Just to set the record
straight. Okay. State Bank of India was
a lender to
Dean. When King Fisher and Dean
merged, State Bank of India became a
lender to King Fisher Alliance. But it
started with Dean. So like that there
were a group of banks from whom King
Fisher had borrowed money. A group of
banks from whom Dean had borrowed money
and then they got combined into one
entity when Dean and King Fisher merged.
Right. Yes. There were times when the
the the sort of support from the finance
minister at that time meant that you
know when I presented to various banks
including state bank that you know the
airline needed money they would
recognize
um uh our financial needs appraise them
correctly through state bank of India
capital markets and then sanction loans
even though the
creditworthiness uh of Kingpisher
Airlines may have been short of norms.
To that extent, I'm grateful. Yes. But
then, you know, I did my bit as well. I
put in 3,000 crores of UB group's money
into King Fisher Allies. You're talking
to me about allegations of siphoning.
You're talking to me about allegations
of misusing Kingfisher Airlines funds
from my lifestyle for Formula 1. Nobody
ever talks about that 3,000 crores I
infused in cash into King Fisher
Airlines to keep it afloat.
my good friend and uh you know probably
the most successful lady entrepreneur
I've known she's like a sister to me
Kiran Mazumar has often said publicly
that Vijay put everything on the line
for king I did but that's not
appreciated that is not
appreciated that's sad but let the
narrative be what it is see you put
everything you had into reviving King
Fisher Airlines because you believed in
the vision. Mhm.
Right. But at the time when you asked
loans
uh the company was not doing that great.
Correct. Right. So you but you still got
loan from the consortium of 17 banks.
Correct.
The reason was they believed in your
vision or the reason that they were
influenced by the by the government to
give you the loan. Yeah. They believed
in the vision. They did their own
appraisals.
Right. And please never forget I gave my
personal guarantee and United Breweries
Holdings Limited also gave its personal
guarantee. If anybody
had okay bad intentions, if anybody had
intentions to divert money, siphon
money, steal money, could
anybody put themselves on a line with a
personal guarantee? Think about it. So
all this narrative of
chore that is why I say in the last 9
years I haven't bothered about changing
this narrative because it is what it is.
It's written by the Indian
media of course prompted by the
government who have had their own press
conferences etc. I mean Samit Patra, the
BJP spokesman called a press conference
and bandied around in front of the
Indian media letters that I had written
to Prime Minister Manuan Singh trying to
establish a
nexus right between me and the prime
minister and alleging some sort of
wrongdoing by the then Congress
um prime minister. I mean one could see
through the political
rhetoric straight away. Why wouldn't any
Indian citizen write to the prime
minister for help?
Fair because I never asked for money. I
asked only for policy changes. Let's go
to the series of events after this. What
happened? What happened? So I'm
quoting just pure research. Okay. Of
quoting whom? quoting pure research of
what's out there on all the newspapers.
So you got a loan from banks and usually
the normal nature of providing such big
loans is people take people give you
this kind of loan against
collateral and in this case bank took
brand name of king fisher as collateral
and gave you the loan. One of the
collaterals. One of the collateral. What
were the other collaterals? Several
other stocks, shares, property. So
stocks and shares, shares, property and
stock and shares which is again quoted
at that time were at the price of
3839 but banks got it at 68.69. You talk
about Kingfisher Alliance shares. Yeah.
What about all the other shares of UBL
and USL?
Nobody talks about that. But they where
do you think they got this 14,000 crores
from? I'm talking about back then like
one minute they have sold assets and
realized 14,100 crores. Yeah. Large part
of which were my shares.
So you have only focused on brand value.
You've forgotten about the shares.
No, I'm suggested wait a minute. I never
suggested that the brand value would
generate 14,000 crores. my shares that
were
pledged. So there's your answer to all
this
narrative. So you're saying that I'm not
saying it's fact. No. So the the facts
are what you are quoting is they took
shares of King Visher Airlines at the
double price because they were also
getting shares of UB. Mhm. That's why
there was some kind of negotiation which
was played on. No, no. It is a multiple
basket of securities.
But still, why would a bank twice the
share price? Look, nobody dreams up a
share value.
Okay, they were
professional merchant bankers including
State Bank of India, capital markets
involved. They arrived at a share value.
The part of the loan package was that
King Fisher's shares in the airline
itself needed to be pledged to the
banks. But that was all not the only
pledge. It was part of a basket. But
then the media chose to focus only on
that. So I would like to ask the legacy
media where did the 14,000 crores come
from? But you made such a halaboo about
share price of Kingfisher Airlines.
Now you see, now do you
see how people pick and choose to
discredit
you? Isn't it pretty evident? Okay. So
then this happened again. A business
decision by banks. They did everything.
There was no influence
involved. It was pure play business
decision by a bank between you and the
banks. You should ask
them this question. You lent the money
on what basis you lend the money they
should answer the question I'm the
receiver first of all and let me clarify
here when you keep saying you borrowed I
never borrowed one na pisa vijay mallaya
has never borrowed a single rupee from
anybody
ever it was king fisher airlines the
running company that borrowed I was a
guarantor there's a big difference and
then the money came in but you still
Kingfish Airlines was still bleeding
whatever the case may be I also put
3,000 crores you put in 3,000 crores you
put in everything and you tried to
revive it and then one series of event
happened
where there was a non-payment of the oil
bills and that's why the oil companies
as started asking you for advanced money
and that shaked you a little bit more
yeah the working capital cycle got
disrupted. M natural. Then there was
another series of event that Kingfisher
Airlines was not able to pay the airport
fees, the landing charges. Listen, when
a company goes through a cash flow
issue, it affects everybody. Yeah. You
cannot isolate one particular creditor
or vendor.
No. So I'm coming if there's a cash
shortage. Okay. It's across the board. H
so across the board then there were
catering companies which were affected
there was no food everybody after one by
one one by one there was non-payment of
certain things cash flow issue did you
at any point did you think that this not
going to work you were still pushing you
still push I was pushing I was
pushing in the hope that the foreign
investment that I had already
negotiated was going to
fractify which I had already agreed
right with James
Hogan. But the permission never came. It
was
sad and I guess my misfortune that 6
months after King Fisher collapsed in
October 2012 that the same Ethi was
granted permission to invest in Jedways.
Okay. Then another thing happened. Okay.
So you were expecting all of this would
happen.
You asked your people, your staff, your
employees to wait. Mhm. That the money
will come in.
Yeah. But they were not paid. The staff
was not paid. Sadly, no. Right. Mhm. But
there's again a statement that your
international employees were getting
paid. Indian employees were not. Mhm.
And the reason is that because
internationally you would have held
accountable in India, you could get away
with anything. Was that the reason? I
didn't know that. But why were you
paying international employees and not
yours? It's very simple. The money was
available through ticket collections in
England. Because money was available,
staff salaries were paid. In India, the
High Court of Karnataka had frozen over
260 crores worth of
cash. Okay. Now, I'd like to focus on
this non-payment of salaries. There has
been a hell of a lot spoken about it.
All
right. Which has pained me no end. It
has seriously pained
me in my track record as chairman of UB
group. I would ask anyone to check on
how I cared for my
employees. I was proud of the care that
I gave to my employees.
Why would it be different for King
Fisher
employees? The company in India had no
money. There was UB's money of 260
crores in the bank with the sorry with
the bank under the control of the
government of Karnataka.
We applied officially and formally to
the IC court please release the sal
money to pay the
salaries. Court said no. Why? The same
banks
objected. The same public sector banks
objected.
Why? Why? Because they said that money
belongs to them. because the company had
defaulted in payments. But as far as I
was
concerned, I asked the court, please
release those monies to pay the employee
salaries. The banks objected, the courts
refused.
But you personally took salary from
Kingfish Airlines 33 crores a year. No,
no, no. I took salary of 33 crores a
year. I wish. Why do they talk about it?
Who talks? Show me the balance sheet
where it's written.
Can you show me? Not the balance sheet,
but the media talks about it. I can show
you an article. Ask the media where's
the balance sheet. So, you never took
salary? I never took 33 crores of
salary. Or did you take any salary when
other people were not getting paid?
Obviously
not. I mean, you really think I'd pay
myself to the exclusion of other less
wellto-do employees? That's what the
world thinks. That's
unfortunate view of the world about
me which is sadly completely false. But
then they all were on the road striking
against you if you would have spoken to
them in a nicer way probably. I don't
know spoken to them try to explain to
them but at the end of the day they did
what they thought was best. They were
under stress. I respect that. I'm not
blaming
anybody. Okay. A couple of people have
said some nasty things which is fine if
they are under
pressure and their livelihood was under
pressure. I fully understand that and I
take it in my stride. But the fact any
suggestion that I willfully did not pay
or that I ignored them and enriched
myself in the process is completely
false.
While all of this was happening,
something really tragic
happened. One of your employees wife
committed a suicide because they were
not able to pay themselves. Were you
aware of that? I became aware of that
and upon investigation
um that was the culmination of a
longstanding
dispute, marital dispute.
It was convenient to blame it on King
Fisher Airlines and non-payment of
salaries. Once again, when people are
under stress and under unpleasant
circumstances, I don't want to um
comment on it uh in an unsavory way. It
would not be right on my part. I mean,
my sympathies are with the family that
um, you know,
lost one of their kin, but I can tell
you that we investigated the matter and
okay, sadly, the tragedy did happen. Uh,
and yes, sadly, equally sadly, that
family had not been paid their salary.
If you'd like to blame it on on me,
fine. I'll take the blame. As I said,
I'm not afraid of taking blame where
blame is due. Now, I can face up to
reality and truth.
Did you feel like you should have said
sorry to employees?
Because you were not condolence letters
for Yeah, but I didn't copy the media.
I wrote a letter of condolence, but I
didn't copy the media.
You know, here was here was what pissed
people off that in your private life,
you were enjoying.
You were buying the Tu Sultan swad. You
were buying cars in the UK. The value of
a Tipu Sultan sword would not have paid
salaries.
The two MercedesBenz cars, the figment
of people's imagination, would not have
paid the salaries.
And if your suggestion is that I should
have laid low in some artificial
way, forget the
employees, forget the
shareholders of all the other
businesses, United Spirits, United
Breweries, MCF,
everybody really. That would have been
very fair, isn't it?
and
behave behave in a manner where my only
asset and liability in life was
kingfisher airlines I had nothing
else that's the way I should have
behaved
right what about the salaries of the
other employees of the other group
companies what about the shareholders of
those
companies what about the future of those
companies and the management of those
companies. So sadly if one company
fails, is it your suggestion that the
whole group must fail?
No, definitely not.
Okay. Everybody loves to talk about the
failure of King Airlines and of
course pin me the blame on me
personally. Forget about everything
else. It is Vijay Malia's failure. Vijay
Malia's failure. Vijay Malaka Chi, Vijay
Malaka Fraud, everything is Vijay
Mallaya. Fine. What
about United Spirits Limited, United
Breweries Limited from where it started
to where I left
off and the wealth creation in the hands
of
shareholders and the wealth creation in
the hands of
employees probably amongst the highest
in India in the corporate sector
highest all
forgotten nobody even refers to it. King
Fisher Island
Malaya that's it the narrative begins
there ends
there. Do you think if you would have
done things differently probably this
side of you would have been more
celebrated than the side which has
gotten once the media
started beginning with one particular
channel whose anchor is
known
right to shout the house
down
right what did I start by saying vija I
want to see you eating jail
food. I want to see you in jail clothes,
etc.,
etc. Started from there. Everybody had
to jump on the
bandwagon. I think in the same time,
because we're talking about events,
somebody
mentioned that you took out 35
million and invested in buying
properties in France. Rubbish. some with
some uh dummy company called I think
Gizmo holding or something like that.
Tell me if I had siphoned King Fer money
to such an extent as people suggest
how would the LN
run on the bank's own admission on the
debt recovery tribunal's own admission
4,999 crores was a debt
right rest is all
interest. His suggestions are that I
have stolen or misused most of that or
all of it. How would the aine
fly if all the money borrowed from the
banks Vijay Malia pocketed? How would
the aine fly?
So all these
allegations and false narratives being
painted by people, if you analyze them,
they make no
sense. What also is not making sense to
me is when the government said that
they're going to support you in 2008,
the FM said that they'll provide the
loan, which they probably did with the
banks. Mhm.
Later in
2011, the union minister of the same
government objection like he started or
they started objecting that you were not
paying even taxes 150 cr was spending
and they started putting you in the
public eye. They were
aras areas.
Nobody is disputing that. But compare my
areas with their India's areas.
Air India's areas were probably 10 times
that of Kingfisher Airlines. That was
because of the stress of the aviation
sector. And why did Air India didn't get
anything and you got everything every
little every little scrutiny happened
with you if Air India was in trouble
more than you which actually was the
case. It's a fact. Yeah, it's a fact.
They were in more they were in a more
daunting situation than yours like the
airline. Yeah, but all the focus was
only King for sure. Why? You should ask
those that why do you think turned on
the spotlights? Why do you think it
happened?
Clearly combination of animosity,
jealousy, whole bunch of factors and you
know once again unproductive things to
to think about you know in life think
positive.
Come on it costed you a whole life in
India. You must have thought about it
hundreds of times. No I'm not. In any
case, since
1988, I've been going to India for less
than 180 days in a
year. All my three children are American
citizens. All have lived outside India,
never in India. My mother has been in
this country for over 30 years. What do
I go back
to? Of course, I will get the most
ceremonial welcome by the Indian media.
Of course, sure I will. My goodness,
it'll be headlines of every single
newspaper. Okay. Okay. So 2012 the
airline got suspended. Non-payment of
multiple things, working capital, cash
flow, everything got really really bad
for you, right? And
then the big bash happened, the birthday
party which is often talked about in
2015.
Go ahead. What happened between 2012 and
2015 with this case? What happened? I'm
asking you what happened during like did
everybody forgot? What did
everybody like they were not bothered
about Kingfisher Airlines or what were
the cases were going on? Of course
everything was going on. Nothing
stopped. M Nothing stopped because
people don't talk about that often. What
happened? Like what was going on?
Nothing was going on. That's when the
willful defaulter and all that. You know
what the willful defaulter is all about,
right? Tell me what is about what banks
call a willful defaulter
of somebody who has the money but won't
pay. Yeah. That's called a willful
deferral. Yeah.
Right. I made four settlement offers to
the banks between 2012 to 2015. Yes.
Which they refused to
accept that nobody knows. What was the
settlement that you were offering? So
many settlement offers including before
the
court. Right. So it was always the
intention to settle. I flew through
Hyderabad and met the chairperson of the
State Bank of India at their training
academy in Hyderabad and offered a
settlement. It was always my intention
to settle. Never did I say I'm not going
to pay.
And why do you think they didn't accept
it? They wanted 14,100 crores. That's
why they didn't accept it then.
They didn't want your 5,000 cr because
they were expecting it to go up. Like
the sale of your assets will be much
higher than whatever. Is that
Yeah. Had they accepted my offer, they
would have got 5,000 crores. Today
they've got 14,100 crores. But is there
any proof do you have where you offered
them settlement and they didn't accept
from 2015? The records of the Supreme
Court of
India. Proof. What better proof than the
records of the Supreme Court of India,
public documents,
so let's say you offered Yeah. nothing
happened. Nobody, not even a needle
moved. It just kept going on. It kept
getting
worse. And you knew this trouble was
going on.
And in
2015, apparently according to the media,
this is where things went down where you
had a grand birthday party. Your 60th
birthday party 18th December. Mhm. 2015,
right? Correct. What happened in that
party? Nothing. It was party
that normal party that I had and I've
had so many of them over the years.
Do you think you wouldn't you shouldn't
have done that party or made it so
public? But
why? Why? Because the whole narrative is
against you. You spending see this is
what a common person would think. If I
was a kingisher employee and I've not
gotten paid for XYZ reason, for let's
say economic factors, business model,
whatever XYZ reason, I'm not getting
paid. My livelihood is dependent on
this. And then I see the promoter of my
company spending millions of dollars or
Enrique Glacias to perform for his
birthday party. I would get
enraged. I want to as an employee at
that point if I'm not gotten if I've not
gotten paid. I don't understand that
there are 50 businesses that you have
built. I understand only one thing that
the promoter of my company is
enjoying on my expense.
the I would agree with everything that
you said except your
last at my
expense. The promoter of the I'm talking
a common person that's asking fair
enough that common person didn't
know that upon objection by the same
banks a Karnataka high court declined to
to agree to drawing readily available
cash to pay the
salaries.
Right. Okay. I agree with you. The
suffering employee would have also said
the man has United Breweries, United
Spirits is none of my
business. Right.
Right. So I could have been a thorough
hypocrite.
I could have come here to London and had
my party and nobody would have even
known,
right?
Yeah. Would that have solved the
problem? No. Okay. But you didn't do
that. You did the public party in India.
It's not public. Sorry. It was by
invitation. But of course, everything
that I do is covered by and I paid for
it
myself. King Fisher Airlines was in no
position to
pay. I paid for it myself.
Maybe in hindsight
now, okay, and we're talking about
December
2015 against an airline that shut in
2012. Mhm. If you're talking about my
birthday party in December 18,
2012, you probably have a more
significant point.
But three years
later in December
2015, okay, a milestone 60th birthday,
right? Still being held against me with
such venom. I don't quite get it. But
okay, maybe it was a mistake. I should
have probably come here to London and
had my party and nobody would have
known. But once again because I was
transparent and lived my life pretty
transparently as I always did the media
latched on to it and bashed me for it.
Fine. So everything in the last 10 or 15
minutes maybe more that you are
questioning me on are Indian media
generated comments and narratives. None
of these are facts. But are you not
apologetic about what happened?
Apologetic. What do I apologize for? For
only to the employ like only for the
employees of that business. For no one
else. After putting 3,000 crores of my
own money into the business, I need to
apologize.
You've been wronged, but so have your
employees of King Fisher. What would you
say to them who lost their jobs, who
still hold angst against
you? If you were directly just talking
to them and not me, what would you tell
them? I would say I'm deeply sorry for
what happened to
them, I would say, I'm deeply sorry
that some of them didn't get paid their
salaries. I have no excuses to
offer. I take full
responsibility. But for those who care
to
listen, there
was money lying in deposit with the
Karnataka High
Court. I specifically applied to court
to pay the salaries of King Shelline
staff. The banks objected and the court
refused the
permission. There was really nothing I
could do beyond that. And what would you
tell those employees who are still
questioning that hey we were in
trouble and you tried everything to get
that money from the court but it didn't
help then why did you go out and party
like a king on your 60th birthday when
we were suffering
uh we need to look at the timeline
here airlines shut down
2012. My 60th birthday was in December
2015. Right?
There was nothing I could do in the
interim to find money to pay the staff
in
particular because any money that could
have been infused theoretically would
have been taken by the
banks because all the assets were
frozen. Did your legal advise you not to
pay? Absolutely not. I told my legal
advisers to find every single avenue to
pay and they and it didn't work. They
couldn't find a way. But ultimately
because of the
freezing all the money was lying under
the control of the court. So we couldn't
touch the money and every penny that you
would have infused just for their
intention to pay your employees would
have still gotten frozen. You see the
court order did not differentiate
between employees and general corporate
purposes.
Any money in the account of the airline
was
frozen. Frozen by the banks, frozen by
tax department, frozen by service tax.
Everything was
frozen. The chunk of available cash was
with the court and that was actually
cash of UBHL,
not Kingfish Airlines cash of United
Breweries Holdings Limited, one of the
cogntos.
UBL said we want to pay King Fel and
staff salaries. Please allow us. The
banks objected and the court did not
give permission. That is
fact. They I I would feel very sad if
somebody said I had no intention to pay
or that I ignored to make the efforts. I
made every single effort I could. Are
you do you ever feel sorry that you
couldn't do anything to give money to
the employees?
Obviously,
but um are you suggesting
that I'm not sorry for what happened to
King Fischer and the collateral damage
that was caused to everybody?
I'm asking you, are
you? I said I was very sad about the
fact that the You were sad but were you
sorry about it?
Sorry. I apologize publicly to everyone
for the failure of King Fisher Airlines.
Till today I am willing to apologize. I
did my very best. I tried very very
hard. I put in my money, blood, sweat,
and tears. It didn't work. Sadly, it
didn't work. I'm very sorry. At the end
of the day,
frankly, it's what I think of myself
when I look at myself in the mirror in
the morning. Have you done good or have
you not done good? Are you a success or
are you a failure? What is the answer?
I'm a big failure according to
Indians. Fine. I'm a big failure. But
when I look at myself in the mirror, I
don't see failure. But does it bother
you?
Who created
one.75 lakh cr of market cap in the in
the alcoholic
business? Who created it? Even after
creating such a behemoth, people think
you're a failed business owner. Fair
enough. So let Does it bother you? And
who made King Fisher Airlines so
public? Who made it?
Dammania airways started and
failed. East West Airlines started and
failed,
right? Jet Airways eventually
failed, right? Modilu started and
failed,
right? Paramount started and
failed. You read about
them only King Fisher and
Malia. Is that not a targeted attack?
Because here's what got crafted after
it. Who crafted it? I'll tell you. I'll
come to that. Tell me then. So, tell me
what about all these other aviation
failures? See, nobody cares about them
because nobody was as public as you. Ah,
so now we're talking that I pay the
price for my own public image and the
fact that you left the country. Ah
that's which is another which is another
uh so I'll come to the series of events
of these both of them no problem okay
so 2015 December this happened before
that CBI started investigating you and I
appeared before the CBI four times h and
CBI concluded their case that they found
you siphoning the money was that the
completely false. Okay. There is no
allegation of money siphoning by CBI.
What did CBI conclude? Nothing. That I
spent on a private jet which was
Kingfish Airlines own assets. Yeah. That
I misrepresented to
IDBI while taking the loan. Mhm. What
did you misrepresent? That I
misrepresented. Uh you asked me a
question about brand valuation, right?
So one of them one of the allegations
brand valuation. Was it also bizarre
like IDBI gave you loan in just 2 days
and on Sunday you got the money
transferred in your bank. Yeah. But then
they that was a short-term loan. Okay.
They got the money back and then they
participated in the consortium lending.
Okay. Yeah. So but there is no
allegation of siphoning money. No. Zero.
So there was misrepresentation. Yeah.
That's and using that money or using the
Kingfisher loan proceedings to buy a
private jet. Not private jet was owned
by King
Airlines. The King Airlines own asset.
They said I misused it. I misused it for
personal trips.
Did
you? I think if you see the line of
private jets starting from Mr.
Aman's
in Bombay airport and ask them who uses
your jets, you'll get the answer.
Come on. Deflecting is not a right way.
Deflecting. I'm asking you. What? Did
you misuse it? What is misuse? I don't
know. Whatever they're quoting, do you
agree with it or no? So, you agree with
the CBI? No, I'm asking you. Do you
agree with it or not? I am not agree
with it. Obviously, I don't agree with
it. You used it for business purposes
only. What do you mean business
purposes? If I had to fly on holiday,
I'd say private
jet. That's what CB had problem with. Is
that the case? Yes. That you you you
took the Come on. That would not only be
the case. Huh? That would be a part of
your case. Let's say you This is what
I'm saying. The principle one was
misrepresentation.
Okay. Yeah. So that is first
misrepresentation and because of this
they issued an
LOC they issued LOC right lookout
circular to the immigration office that
should not leave the country no I'm not
aware of any of that okay because then
there was a public issuance against in
2015 where the LOC which was issued for
you had few words changed I know nothing
about this okay so there
And this I'm quoting
from again another article where I can
show you the article where it's I've
never heard of this before. Okay. So the
article said that you met with someone
really powerful and after that in just
few months the lookout circular got
changed and the lookout circular changed
into okay next time to the immigration
off officers that if Vijay Malia comes
to the airport and want to leave the
country you need to inform us where is
he going and for what purposes you don't
need to stop him but earlier the
CBI put out a lookout notice that you
should not allow Vijay Malia to leave
the country and this change was made in
2015. I know nothing about this. This is
the first time you are informing me. I
went in and out multiple times during
the never never a problem at
all and what you're telling me now is
news to
me. I've never known of LOC issued or
any other form of notice. The changed
happened on 24th November 2015. Just few
words and it specifically read this was
a fresh LOC that he needs to be
questioned before leaving the country.
Where is he going and needs to and this
needs to be informed to CBI after that
he can continue traveling. He should not
be stopped. That's fine. that you said
when in 2015
24th November 2015 a fresh LOC was and
before that before that there was just I
don't have must have gone in four times
before that two oh so then where's the
LOC
so all of this is random thing that you
met someone really powerful in Delhi and
got changed and you changed your CBI
circular or something
nonsense Okay. Then another thing then
another series of event happened because
after your public birthday party people
started
uh losing their [ __ ] They started
getting they started getting pissed. It
became even more public. This 2015 end
of
it your Supreme Court interfered. I
guess Supreme Court entered in this
whole case and they put up a bench that
3rd March
your case needs to be heard or needs to
be represented in front of Supreme
Court. On 1st March 2016,
you I think you were in Delhi, you went
to the parliament and 2nd March you left
the country one day before when you were
about to be present in front of Supreme
Court. Is all of this real or none of it
is real? No, no, this is completely
false. There was no Supreme Court
hearing. I was not summoned to court. I
I'm not aware of any court hearing.
I told the finance minister Arun
Jetley before leaving for the
airport and then I flew from Delhi to
London. I was on my way to Geneva for a
FIA world council meeting which was
fixed months ago. I told the finance
minister because I went from parliament
to Delhi
airport when this
news hit the
media once
again it created a storm.
Yeah. People went running to Mr. Jetley.
He denied meeting
me. A Congress MP saw us and then said
to the media, "No, I saw them
together." Mr. Jetley had to retract his
statement and yes, yes, I met him, but
only while I was walking. It was a
fleeting
meeting. I never said I went to Mr.
Jetley's office, sat in front of him,
had tea with him.
All I said is I told the finance
minister while leaving I'm going to
London. I have to go to Geneva for a
meeting. I'll be back. Please tell the
banks to sit across the table and settle
with me. How long does this take this
one sentence? A minute or two.
But you see the way he denied it. Then
when the Congress MP pointed out his
mistake that he saw us, he quickly
changed. This is the problem with the
media. Particularly where I'm concerned.
They conjure up stuff. They blow things
well out of
proportion. Okay? If it's good for their
business, let them continue doing it. So
all of this is nuisance that on 2nd of
March you left Delhi airport for London
in a jet airways flight 9W122 from T3
with 55 big
suitcases and somebody says 27, somebody
says 55. I mean different newspapers,
different
stuff. What difference does it make?
They say LOC then they say no LOC then I
tell the finance minister I'm going then
he says no then he says no he had a
fleeting meeting with
me and all this 15 18 suitcases were
complete and utter rubbish. So your
intention was never to leave the
country.
Look please understand this whole
narrative of Bhagya Bhaga because this
is where it starts. Yeah,
this is coming from people who don't
know their facts. Tell us the facts.
I came to England in
1988. I got my indefinite leave to
remain ILR in 1992.
For 32 years, I have been a permanent
resident of the
UK allowed only to spend 180 days in
India because I have preserved my
non-resident status since 1988.
All right, that is why I used to go back
and forth so
often. All
right. So I came I was attending a
scheduled meeting in Geneva like I told
you. What happened? The loudest anchor
in the television
industry
started all the media piled
on. Huge hungama. How did Vijay Mala
leave? How did he leave? like any normal
person on a jet airways
flight that too after telling the
finance minister that I'm
going driving from parliament house to
the
airport right so this whole tamasha
started right how does
government normally react to media
frenzy check your own
facts I said okay let things cool
On top of
that,
I was negotiating with my foreign
collaborators to sell certain shares so
that I could pay the banks. My intention
was always to settle with the
banks. Right. Yeah. So, I told I wrote
to the enforcement directorate who sent
me a summon. I need some time. I'm
negotiating. I want to settle with the
banks. I've got some business to do.
I've already appeared before the CBI. I
will of course I will appear before you.
Right. Just give me some time. What
happened in the meantime? They revoked
my
passport. Revoked it.
When When was this revoking? 2016. Oh,
right before you left.
Before. Right after you left. Yeah.
Passport gone. How to travel?
So you got stuck because they revoked
your passport. Your intention was to
come back to
country. Many things may have been
different. No. But your intention was
without without a passport. Where do you
go? Nowhere. Correct.
Because you were a British citizen. Not
citizen. Permanent res. Permanent
resident. I kept my Indian passport
because I was a member of parliament.
Okay. which I could not be a member of
parliament had I not been an Indian
citizen.
So if your intention was to come back to
the country why didn't people allow you
look that you should ask the
people why should I sit and speculate
but aren't they spending millions of
dollars in cases to get your extradition
done?
Yes. because they have to make a show of
things as well.
No, have
I
please? Let's be very
clear. Can
somebody from the
government say to the public, "What
crime have I committed for which I must
be
investigated? Have I stolen money from
the banks?
You must have a primacy case that I've
stolen. You can't just make it up in
your head. Yeah. That I've stolen money
from the banks. You need some primacy
evidence.
Have I done any money
laundering? Have I done any drug
smuggling? Have I been involved in any
violent crime?
What
is the allegation against Vijay
Mallaya? Nobody can have an allegation
against Vijay Mallaya of dishonesty
because I have always been honest and
truthful. I have never
borrowed and I have never cheated and I
never will.
But you got this tag of willful
defaulter. Willful defaulter is a
person who can pay and who doesn't pay.
That's a
crime. That's
crime, isn't it? Make up your
mind. Then why did you freeze all my
assets? You froze my
assets. Okay. In 2016,
right? That's how you've recovered
14,100 crores,
right? You can't freeze
assets of a
person on one hand and call him a chore
on the other hand. See, they call you
willful defaulter because you had money
and you didn't pay. And that's why they
had to take such a strict action to
freeze your assets. If you would have
paid earlier then they would have not
done this. But if you're saying that
from 2012 to 2015 you have applied
multiple times in the court that you
want to settle. Yes.
Why is all of this
happening? I think it's very clear it's
also been a part of the media where a
particular senior officer of the state
bank of India said to a good friend of
mine that as a banker I would have
settled with Vijay a long time ago but
if I do any settlement with him I'll
have the CBI on my neck the very next
day. And why do you think CBI has to do
all of these
things? Because technically banks,
you're saying banks want 14,000 cr.
Isn't the CBI called a cage parrot?
But then banks ultimately want 14,000
cr. So they don't want anything to
happen. Why would bank want to settle?
Who knows? Who knows? If you go to the
banks today, they may tell you I owe
even more money. Tell me real numbers
because somewhere it's written 9,000 K
or somewhere it's written there is no
9,000 that is all
imagination
6203 is the real number judgment debt
6203 6,23
and you have been vocal about it I was
going through your tweets publicly you
have been very vocal about that hey I
want to pay come talk to me hey I want
to settle there are multiple times
you've just said it I have show you
letters I've written to the banks
nothing we cannot engage with you period
right you were part of the parliament
Mhm. And you had you were influential.
You had money. You were
powerful. You could do nothing about all
of
this. What went
wrong? That probably is the cause of
everything that
followed. Who do you make a poster boy?
Somebody who is insignificant. Is it?
Why would if you want to if you want to
make an example of somebody who do you
make an example of a visible person or
an invisible person? Definitely a
visible person. Correct. So there you
have got the answer. But why would they
want to make an example out of you when
you were ready to settle? It was just a
business failure in your terms. It it
suits you no to reject a settlement
offer and to continue to claim that
amounts are due to the banks and you
therefore you're a defaulter and
therefore we are going to hound you and
chase
you. It suits the
narrative today in
India business failure means fraud.
If purely that line you're talking about
asking me about
me, why
people tag me woolful defaulter? Why
they accuse me? Why the narrative is so
negative about me? What happened to poor
Nar Goyel? What
happened? India's biggest airlines jet
collapsed. Naresh Goyel went to jail.
What happened to people like Gautam
Tapur in
Delhi in jail?
Right? So if your business does badly,
you're automatically referred to as a
fraud. The inference is that you have
stolen. In which countries does this
happen?
The biggest companies in the world
fail, right? Are
there their management, senior
management put in
jail? Are they accused of
fraud? The whole purpose of
business is associated with certain risk
as well. Y right.
But in India, sadly, you have a business
that
fails. You're accused of fraud and
improper conduct.
And people say and the government and
the agencies
that your fraud or people who are
businesses have failed are
fraud because they've taken money from
the banks which is a common taxpayers
money which is common people's money. So
if you take common people's money and
you're not able to repay it then you're
considered
wrong. But if in your case if they have
actually recovered more than 2.5x of it
or probably somewhere around that
number why are they still behind you?
Because as I
said, have you ever
heard of
any
bank not rendering an account to a
borrower or a
guaranter? Despite 15
reminders, the same
banks have not given me a statement of
account. Not one. Have you ever heard of
such conduct anywhere in the world? For
the first
time, it is through the statement in
parliament of the finance
minister and the printed report of the
ministry of
finance that they have shown 14,100
crores recovered from me. The government
have the banks have not rendered a
statement of account. That is why I have
gone to the Karnataka High Court asking
the court to direct the banks to give me
a statement of account. That is the
pitiful state of affairs. Now let me
explain things to you very in a summary
fashion in this entire debt of
Kingfisher Airlines and the recovery.
You have the recovery officer of the
debt recovery tribunal. Yeah. The debt
recovery tribunal is the one that that
that gave the certificate of debt. They
have recovery officers whose job it is
to recover against that recovery
certificate and inform the tribunal
about how much has been recovered
because when the full amount is
recovered the debt recovery tribunal
will issue a discharge certificate that
your debt is paid. Second is because the
second guarantor United Breweries
Holdings Limited is in
liquidation. It is in the control of the
official
liquidator. The official liquidator is
also obliged to give an account to the
court right on the liquidation which
includes being a co-arer of the king
fisher airlines debt
right both
these have stated in court in judicial
proceedings that the banks have been
fully
paid yet the banks have not submitted a
statement of account. I have had to go
to the Karnataka High
Court pleading with them to please
direct the banks to submit a statement
of account and of course the official
liquidator and the recovery officer as
well. This is the conduct of those banks
and you're asking me questions about why
they didn't do this and why they didn't
do that. Does it happen with other
entrepreneurs as well? I'd be shocked if
it did. I've never heard of anything
like this. Do you think the Indian
system gets rigged against the
entrepreneurs or the business owners who
get too powerful after a point? It's
certainly rigable because in your case,
this is what happened, right?
In my case, all the
facts are there for everyone to see.
Then sir, what's the future? Like what
what's going to happen now? What's
happening in your story?
What you're telling is completely
different than anything and everything
that any Indian person out there who
will do little research about you would
find. It's completely different than
what you're telling. But if you do
research on me, what are you going to
find?
You will only find the
narrative generated over a period of
time by the Indian legacy media and to
certain extent the
government and what they have
said and of course when I say government
it includes CBI and ED and this that and
the other. All right, that's all you
will
find. All of which is false
narrative either deliberately
written or in some cases with the media
ignorately written. So is there a
businessman, politician, media kind of
nexus against you in India? I don't know
who is against me except this
government and I made no bones about it
that I am their poster boy. I am also a
political football,
right? You must have heard the the
narrative. BJP tells Congressw.
Congress responds to
[Music]
BJP is the football in the
middle. What is the biggest challenge of
doing business in India?
government
extreme government it's in the Indian
DNA no matter what a state government or
a federal government may say about ease
of doing business in India there is no
ease of doing business in India there
are hurdles bureaucratic hurdles
political hurdles all along the way they
may have reduced over a period of time
uh but but no I mean you can't compare
India and ease of doing business in
India with any of the western economies.
But how did you manage that before? Like
earlier you expanded your group from
couple of hundred crores to thousands of
critically you must be navigating
somehow with all these challenges. What
did you do? That's what I said. I I had
to maintain good relations with almost
29 countries. That's a 29 states all of
which were empowered by the constitution
to have their own policy on liquor. So I
had to effectively be in the good books
of 29 chief ministers. What do you mean
by becoming or getting in the good books
of the government? Well, you know, like
were you doing favors? They were asking
favors to you.
Look, let me tell
you when elections were announced, I
would desperately want to take a holiday
outside India. Why? Because I didn't
want to be accessible. The politicians
always felt that you know the liquor
business was the cash cow that would
meet their electoral aspirations. um you
know sometimes these aspirations were
completely unreasonable and
impractical but no I mean
look dealing with government doesn't
mean underhand exchange of
money okay it definitely doesn't I mean
whoever said that you know I can buy my
way through X Y or Z is wrong okay you
can have good relations with people and
provided you present
um a proposal to them that meets their
own political objectives, it works well.
But would there ever be exchange under
the table as well? All of that used to
work. No, you
know, I'm not going to confirm or deny
that because I leave it to your
imagination because I think you know
India as much as I know
India and
They would ask for backing the election
campaigns. That's what they would ask
technically. Or were there was there
something else as well? Look, the
demands were varied. Give me give me
example of two three demands. The
demands were first of all cash. Second
copious amounts of alcohol which is
seems to be an essential part of any
electoral campaign for free. Vehicles.
Vehicles. Cars. vehicles, jeeps, cars.
Yeah. So it was
multifarious but the easiest for me was
to disbuzz alcohol. M which is you know
at the end of the day I was in a
privileged position heading India's
largest alcohol company. I could say all
right fine you know but yeah alcohol
plays a big role in elections in India
even today.
How do you make money now?
How do I make money? Like today, how do
you make money? I make a I I get a
modest salary from my company.
Not the Indian companies.
No. So you like do you own anything
here? There are companies here or in
other countries? Of course. I told you
I've been a non-resident since
1988. Okay. Uh even though I sold Bger
paints in 1996, I've had several other
businesses outside of
India for the last 30 years. What was
your net worth at peak in India? I don't
know because it fluctuated with the
share value any number to great amount
of speculation. Okay.
Frankly, what difference does it make?
What's in it worth today? I don't know.
probably zero according to the banks
probably. Walk me through your day
today. What do you do now after all of
this and done? What time do you wake up?
How do you keep yourself busy? What do
you do? Well, I have six dogs. I love
them. I love dogs. I play with them. I
like to keep a breast of international
news.
Um,
I love my dogs. I play with them a lot.
Uh, I have a few classic cars which I
like to tinker with, but I have an
office on the property next door with my
staff and yeah, as I told you, I have
running
businesses and so I keep an eye on them,
but sadly a lot of time is taken on
unproductive and very expensive legal
matters.
Um sadly once again the
banks in India who
are stateowned banks public sector
banks carried their attack on me here
even before the UK
courts. So as if Indian legal
proceedings were not enough they even
came here. M fine. So, I have to defend
myself.
And the businesses that you run here,
they fund the legal fees and everything
that you're doing. Yeah. There's, let's
put it this way, there's enough to go
around.
What kind of businesses are here? The
same brewery or something else. Oh,
yeah. Yeah. Basically, save my core
business, alcohol brewery or all that.
You love it. You love doing the same
thing. That's what's in my blood. You
know, I used to joke when I was young. I
said I was born in a bottle.
Wow. Do you feel restricted
now? Because you just use word I was
born in a bottle. Do you feel that
you've been caged in a bottle again with
all these legal matters because you
don't have a passport.
You're a free bird flying around all
over the world. Yeah. So now you're
stuck here. But that freedom went in
2016 when the Indian government revoked
my passport.
So it wasn't a
suspension, it was a
revocation. So I
knew back
then the consequence was no trouble,
right?
So for a guy who used to be on a plane
three four times a week flying around
the
world to be in one country for nine long
years certainly a game
changer. It must be
but it's not a matter of life and death.
I mean it isn't that
profound because there's enough and more
to do and to enjoy a quality of
life that okay has shrunk in many
ways from what used to be but it's still
okay one must get on and move on. Does
it not bother you?
No. Do I well I it doesn't bother me. Do
I look bothered?
No, not to me. It's not a question of
what is the meaning of do I get up in
the morning and wipe my tears away every
day? No. Someday some point you're like
I'm done with this. Like what the hell
is happening with me? What is my
solution? What are my
options? The government of India has
revoked my
passport. Right?
All I can get is a one-way travel pass
to India. That's it. What about my
constitutional
rights that every Indian citizen is
entitled to a
passport? And what happens if I try to
enforce those? It'll drag on for years
in the court by the time I might be too
old to travel.
So don't you feel lonely here? No. Well,
I have a lot of my friends
uh here in England. I lot of people come
and visit
me. Uh well, another one of life's
lessons is when times are tough, you
realize who your actual friends are.
Then I have realized
that very
comprehensively. I mean those who used
to be my so-called buddies who
uh in times of
my heyday for lack of a better word and
nowhere to be said. So you used to hang
out with a lot of billionaires,
Bollywood celebrities, politicians, lot
of people and your friends from the
corporate world. They all stopped taking
up your calls. No, no, no, no. The
politicians certainly
stopped. And I think as one one of the
many politicians explained to me quite
truthfully, which I respect, he said if
we are seen to be associated with Jews,
this government will come after us, you
know, because I think there in the
political world, I think it's pretty
well known and more importantly pretty
obvious that this government is after
me. M
um so they want to protect
themselves as far as
uh corporate titans are concerned I mean
Kiran Mazumar bless her soul she's like
my sister makes it a point to be in
constant
touch comes to England we always have a
meal together and like that there are
few other good
friends who keep in touch but
Otherwise
no certainly not as frequently as I
would have been in touch with them or
seen them when I was in India and all
these troubles hadn't started. Talk
about Kiran Mazumar Sha she publicly
talks about you and how close you were
like since childhood you were friends
and she talks about your generosity your
optimism. She's been very vocal that you
gave it all to save and fight it all.
You she has gone out in public and said
that just it was bad times and bad
things which happened to you but you
were right and you gave it all away. So
she talks about it and someone of that
stature living in a very public market
in country like India usually people
stay away from these conversations and
people would want to she talks but she
doesn't she talks about it everyone
every time people ask about you she's
been okay about it in fact there was a
statement that she said lot of people
are optimistic which I was probably
rather more optimistic than most and
version of just optimism. Let me tell
you, Kiran and me grew up together. I
talked about the brewery house in
Bangalore. At that time there was a
little colony. So there was a brewery
house in which I lived and then four
other bungalows. The one next to the
brewery house was actually occupied by
Kiran Mazuman and her father. Her father
was the chief brewer and the technical
director of UB. Okay. Okay.
And so Kiran and her two brothers and
mom grew up in my house in my in my
colony with one wall separating us. So
we were very very close uh and
and Kiran has been very very
different. She started off being a
qualified brew master.
How many Indian
women can you think of who would go and
qualify as a brew
master? But Kiran was determined to do
it and she did it in Australia.
So Kiran as an
entrepreneur not only has been brilliant
but has a super brilliant track
record but she's a tough cookie and she
speaks her mind which is something that
people should
respect and being a woman at that. So
I'm so grateful for her public support
of me. She knows what I went through
with Kingfisher Airlines. I used to
share it with her all the time. And she
knew that I gave it my all. I forget
about just putting in 3,000 crores. I
mean,
every bit of my blood, sweat, and tears
went into trying to make King Fisher
Airlines
work. Now that she isn't here, you're
not
there. You're alone. friends, parties,
uh businesses, that busy, restless life,
nothing is
there. In 9 years, what was the
loneliest day of your life?
I I always have had something to do. I
haven't been
sitting alone. Uh I told you I my
interests keep me occupied. My pace of
life is slowed down
dramatically. My pace of life now is
probably one of
semi-retirement to be
honest. But that's what
happens when you reach retirement age,
isn't
it? So the frenzy of the
past doesn't last
forever. And I'm in that phase.
But I have enough and more interest to
keep me occupied.
What do people misunderstand about you?
I don't know what people understand to
begin with. Forget about
misunderstanding. I
mean, people in general, particularly
the media, they hate my guts.
They don't like the fact that I rarely
get
flustered and they try to break me down
deliberately brick by brick. They try
very very hard but you know maybe it's
my upbringing in life. Maybe because I
started very
young. I'm
tough and tough so I don't get brow
beats. I don't get pushed over. I stand
my ground.
And the media hate
it. They absolutely hate it. So I've
heard all this. Malia is arrogant. Malia
is a show off X Y and Z. And the
narrative keeps repeating time and time
and time
again
because I have never taken out my
handkerchief and started weeping in
front of them.
They would love that. If I did that in
front of the legacy media, probably the
whole narrative about me would change.
But that's not me. Is this also has this
become your defense mechanism now? There
was never any defense mechanism. Like
now it has become your image that hey I
don't get I'm not going to break in
front of you guys. So I'm going to stick
through it and that's why I won't show
my real side. I won't show my real
emotions. I won't show what I'm feeling.
But what I'm feeling is real. There is
no other side. There is no other
side. Please
understand for 50
years. I've been in charge. I've been
through a
lot. I've been there, done that. He's
toughened me
up. I faced the crisis of Kingfisher
Airlines. I felt it more than anybody
else. I gave it my all, but I kept
myself together because I was a
leader. If I had crumbled and collapsed,
the airline would have crumbled and
collapsed a lot earlier than it did.
What are you feeling right now as you
talk about you gave it all and you still
couldn't save King Fisher? Well, I'm I'm
sad about it because you know it's not
just about King
Fisher. I have never been used to
business failure.
I took risks. I made bold decisions and
I built my core business in alcohol into
something I could be greatly proud
of. I failed with Kingfisher and that
hurts me more than anything else.
Kingfisher was a wonderful product,
probably the most awarded airline
ever, providing connectivity to places
in India that were never connected by
air
before and in an
environment
promising
growth. Today, India is the biggest
single growth market for aviation in the
world.
Can you imagine if King Fcher was still
flying? It was just circumstances at
that particular time, government
policies that didn't
help and mounting
losses. But I gave it my all. I I told
you quite apart from putting in 3,000
crores cash into Kingfisher
Airlines and the final straw was the
refusal to let Etihad invest in King
Fisha and that was it. I had run out of
options. Can you imagine how I
felt? I felt miserable. What's your
biggest fear now? My fear? Are you
afraid of anything?
Well, what can I be afraid
of? What can I be afraid of? What do I
do that would scare
me? Living a semi-retired life, what can
happen that's going to
uh scare me? Extradition.
Oh, yeah.
Look, if you're talking about the legal
issues, there are multiple legal issues.
All right,
which I will
defend before the courts of law both in
this country as well as in
India.
And any legal case can go either way.
You can't sit and predict the
outcome. Neither can you celebrate a
potential outcome and neither can you
cry about a potential outcome. That's
what legal cases are all about. But are
you prepared for the worst? Of course, I
have to face the worst. I
I no qualms or no doubts in my mind that
if the worst is what is destined for me,
that's what's destined for me and you
face it head on. What do you think is
worst? What is what can happen the
worst? Oh, what I think is very clear,
what the Indian government wants, what
many of the Indian media anchors want,
jail
clothes, jail
food in Thihar or Arur Road or God knows
which jail in India. That's it. And
spend the rest of my life behind
bars. That's it. Have you ever imagined
yourself actually going to jail? Well,
if that's what is inevitable, what
option do I have? Is it inevitable?
Might
be. I'm not an
astrologer. I'll fight my way in court.
Doesn't it scare you that I lived a
king-sized life and now I might end up
in jail? Uh, and those that is how I'm
going to end my life like probably.
Correct. So, I said earlier today,
right? hero to zero
and you're okay with it. What option do
I have? Do you ever wake up and think
like [ __ ] why me? What is this
happening? Because in your head you're
clear and you say that you've not done
anything wrong. So do you ever feel like
why the hell me? Maybe that's my
destiny. Maybe my stars are misalignant.
Do you believe in it?
No. I don't believe in
astrology. But do you believe in God? In
God very much so. I'm deeply religious.
I have gone to most of the temples in
India particularly South India. I've
made my modest
offerings to various temples. I I don't
know whether you know but the Sabriala
temple in Kerala the
entire gold roof was donated by
me. Tirupati
Tirumala temple uh the entire gold
plating of the front of the sanctum was
donated by me. I've donated dwaja tambas
in the subramanya temple and moambika
temple.
I Yeah. So I I definitely believe in
God. Do you not then question it? No, I
don't question it. I just I just I
believe like I believe in God so much. I
do so much for my religious belief and
still I'm going through all of this.
Yeah. Well, ultimately God will protect
me. That if I have to have a rough
ride in the process, maybe that was also
what God wants. Do you think winning the
case is important for you now? Or you're
like, even if it gets stretched, I've
come terms to my life. I'm aging. It's
okay.
Unfortunately, the word stretch doesn't
work in English
courts. Okay. There's nothing known as
stretching a case in this country. In
India, yes, sadly, that's why legal
matters take so much time to resolve.
Here, dates fix, trial, it's fixed,
decision rendered, story
over. So, you can't willfully kind of
string things along. But is it important
for you to win?
Yes, because I believe I should win on
merit. What have I done? I've done
nothing
wrong. I haven't I'm not a criminal. If
you could go back to your younger self,
what would you tell your younger self?
Would you tell him to do anything
differently? I think the values I've
instilled in
my my son in particular and my all my
three children is by example my hard
work. They have of course they were very
young but they've seen how hard I
worked and basically the dedication and
commitment to your objectives and your
responsibilities. That's it. But would
you go to your younger self and tell
something different? What could what
what choices would I have? If you gave
me a choice on what I would choose, I
might choose. But if I was probably
never start Kingfisher Airlines because
that all cost you the trouble. Yeah,
good possibility. Good possibility that
maybe I should have just said I'm going
to stick to my core business of alcohol
and just not do anything else. Do you
think any part of it you would have
dealt
with little in a different
way anything about you about the choices
you've made? Yeah, maybe I made one
wrong choice in listening to the finance
minister Mr. Prana Mukhaji when I went
to him I realized the writing was on the
wall. They were very tough times and I
told him I have to downsize this
airline and he said no no no you cannot
and the banks will support you and so on
and so forth and yeah I I listened to
him maybe I shouldn't have I should have
gone ahead and downsized it and had I
downsized it the financial burden would
have been far less and probably king
Fischer would have been flying till
today what's one thing about extreme
wealth
that people common people don't
understand.
I don't know because I've never had
extreme wealth uh ever.
The kind of wealth you had was extreme
for a large share of people around the
world, not just our country. Once again,
a major
misconception. Just because I had the
Kingfisher calendar with pretty
models. Just because I I sponsored the
Indian Derby in horse
racing. Just because I sponsored
fashion. All of which were to my mind
marketing tools with the singular
objective of promoting my brands. And I
got the tag of king of good times which
gave the impression that I was super
rich. I didn't spend a penny from my
pocket. None. But you were super rich.
You still are super rich. I'm not. All
my
assets in India have been
taken. Right. So yes, there were
thousands of
crone. Right? So what do I have left?
That's India. Here you're sitting in my
house. I've explained my
lifestyle. It's
normal. What's super rich about
it? Come on. This is super. What's super
rich about it? This is super rich. Let's
just agree to disagree here because come
on. Like what are we even talking about?
This is not a life of somebody a normal
taxpayer or a normal person going to a
job or 99% of the people in the world.
Were you ever in control of your public
image? Why I never even tried?
Because what you're telling the version
that I get to see in last two days and
what probably millions of people would
get to see now
is a version that is completely
different that is out there. That's why
I'm doing the podcast with you. You
built a personal brand which crashed
down way worse than King Fisher
Airlines.
Did you ever make it or it was always
just the media who did it? It was always
the media who did it. So you were never
control of your personal brand ever at
any point? Not
once. Never even paid attention to it.
And you never bothered.
No. Why should I bother? And why bother
now?
Absolutely correct.
But what's going on? Like
why why do you care now? Because I'm not
talking about brand Vijay Mallaya. I'm
talking about how I have been
wronged. I'd like to show you something.
All right. Here
is here is the recovery certificate of
the debt recovery tribunal. Right? It
says recovery
certificate
6,23 crores 35 lakhs
3,879 and Pisa 42 only.
That's the
6,23 crores plus interest at 11.5% with
yearly
rests. All right. So that
is that is
evidence of the debt. Right? Okay. You
asked me
earlier where did this 9,000 cr figure
come from?
This is the official debt recovery
tribunal Karnataka Bangalore's
document that's and they have said that
you owe 6,2003 cr rupees me along with
four others four others yeah correct
okay kingfisher airlines United Beries
Vijay Malia Kingfisher fine west correct
okay so the assets of all those
combined
right would need to satisfy the judgment
debt of 6,0002 crores. Yeah. Before I go
very further, I'm the one under attack.
Not all four. Anyway, you ask me about
where this 9,000 figure came from. Yeah,
because it's written 6,2003.
No problem. Plus interest, whatever the
case may be. That is dated 2017. If you
see the date of the document.
Yeah, I can't. Where is this? Maybe you
should go to the end. Okay. Last
signing. Yeah. Date of
deliveries 26 July 17. Correct. Okay.
And
then I'll show you
another report about an interview with
the prime
minister. Okay.
March
29,
2019 in
which the prime
minister has
said he owed 9,000
cr but government recovered 14,000 cr
says PM Modi on India's action against
Vijay Malia.
Yeah.
But so why would a PM say 9,000 cr where
this
number? I am as perplexed as you
are because the banks have not ever
submitted a statement of account to me
which in itself is very
strange but the prime minister has said
it and it has been widely
reported all
right and it quotes the figure of 9,000
crores
now the prime minister of India is not
going to make a frivolous statement.
Somebody must have told him number
but I wonder if there was no keen
governmental interest in
me. It's not normal for a prime minister
of the world's largest
democracy to be talking about a recovery
from a guarantor called Vijay Malia. He
addressed it because your case was very
public and a lot of people were
questioning it. You became a public
matter. You were no more a
private defaulter. So I'm the only one
according to you. No, you were too way
too public than others. There are
several other companies who have
borrowed a lot more money. uh I mean a
lot seriously a lot more money but
nobody gets mentioned anyway that's fine
I'm just narrating the sequence of
events
then be before we go there
who are you actually fighting against
media government or judiciary I'm not in
uh court against the
media I'm not in court
against the judiciary. I can't be I'm
defending
myself from those who are prosecuting me
and the prosecutor is either the
government or the
bank.
Simple.
Okay, I'll go through the series of
events. Let's go through those events
together. One of the sort of allegations
is that I
improperly borrowed money from the IDBI
bank
by some sort of nexus. Yeah. Between you
and the general manager and no no the
chairman and managing director and
executive directors which is a lot of
people were involved so that the normal
rules of lending were not applicable to
you. IDBI Bank had a Reserve Bank of
India and a
um Ministry of Finance representative on
their board. All the loans that King
Airlines received were approved by their
board. Right. M
that I will draw your
attention
to public statement in
2021 because IDBI is a publicly listed
entity had to report their financial
performance to the stock
exchange and announcing the quarter 1
results the managing director and CEO MK
Sharma Um said that
278 crores by way of
principle and 331 crores by way of
interest aggregating
753 crores was recovered from Kingfisher
Airlines. This is in
2021 and therefore IDBI was paid in
full.
Then
why why does CBI and ED find you guilty?
Because once they file their charge
sheets, the presumption is that you are
guilty until you prove yourself
innocent. Whereas the law requires the
opposite. You are presumed innocent
until they prove you guilty.
I'm still waiting for the CBI and
enforcement
directors to produce evidence of my
guilt, but they continue to pursue me on
behalf of the banks.
Now, you see
here,
right, the this follows the finance
minister statement in parliament on the
floor of parliament.
on December 17th, 2024, which is a few
months
ago. But here is the annual
report of the Ministry of Finance
printed hard copy for the year
2425 in which they say under 4.2.14
2.14 restitution of properties to
victims of money
laundering/ legitimate
claimments. Okay. And it goes on to say
the enforcement directorate is not only
actively pursuing the economic offenders
to unravel the money laundering but at
the same time is also making efforts for
the restitution or return of assets to
the banks and others who have been
defrauded by the
offenders. Right. The ED has
successfully restored properties valued
at approximately rupees
22,280 crores to victims or legitimate
claimments. The details of the
restitution/restoration done by ED are
given below. Number one, Vijay Mallaya
case quantum of properties restored
14,131.6
six crores and in the comment section
details of
restoration says complete amount of
attached properties have been
successfully restored to the public
sector banks.
How did they recover 14,000 cr? What did
they sell? What did they do?
They have not given me a statement of
account. So you don't know what property
shares have been sold. We talked earlier
about the properties that were given to
them, right?
So everything the give walk me through
it again if you can please.
What were the things that how did they
recover 14,000 all my assets and
highlight two or three
shares which got like 14
properties everything they attached and
they've sold but in the absence of a
statement of account can you believe it
right that from
2017 the date of the DRT order till
today
2025 the banks have not given me a
statement of
account how
much recovery they made on which date,
how much interest they have charged, how
the interest gets reduced because of
recoveries made etc. and what the net
position is
nothing reminders to the
banks from my English lawyers remain
unanswered.
letters from me personally to the
chairman of the SBI remains unanswered
and my last letter requesting a meeting
to resolve these issues came back with
the response saying we are not
interested in
meeting. I have had to go to the
Karnataka High
Court to request the court to direct the
banks to give me a statement of
account. Is this normal?
Do you think there is another
um example like this anywhere in the
world? I mean, it's
ridiculous. So, if I'm not
targeted, then why am I being treated
like this? But
recovering all the money that you owed
is not as same as you paying them
willfully. These are two different
things. Yes. So maybe you I made four
different settlement offers from in
writing from when to when to around 2016
including before the Supreme Court of
India which the banks dismissed before
you left the country you made this. Yes.
Yes.
Absolutely. Absolutely. I've been trying
to settle with the banks. Do you have
that proof? Yeah. It's public record.
Supreme Court of India records.
Absolutely. I would also like to remind
you I told the finance minister that I
was leaving in 2016 and March and told
him that puri please facilitate
meeting with the banks to settle this
loan issue. You know here's something
that don't add up for me. On 29th
February
2016, Supreme Court announced
that the plea seeking action against
Vijay Malia would be heard on March
3 and you left on March 2nd. I'm not
aware of this Supreme Court directive.
How is it possible? Somebody from inside
must have told you something because if
a Supreme Court declares a date against
you. Mhm. How were you not aware? You
were already fighting. There were
lawyers after lawyers. I'm sure there
must be something because there was no
such Supreme Court directive. Simple.
But it's out there in every media
everywhere. But it's written like if you
go back if you if you search today all
the newspapers online everything that
you see it's said that on 29th February
Supreme Court directed that and you left
on March second but my world council
meeting
okay
obligation and appointment was fixed 3
months before that
that is okay I'm not saying that so that
was already a wellestablished travel
plan I once again remind you I told the
finance minister himself on the day of
my departure but that doesn't mean that
you were not aware of this
of what I'm I'm sorry I don't get it
aware of the fact that Supreme Court has
a hearing against you on March 3rd
absolutely not there was no such
hearing there was no such hearing
Supreme Court has said this all Right.
So like I have provided you documentary
evidence. If I'm shown a piece of paper
that states that there was a Supreme
Court hearing in my case scheduled on
the day of my departure, I March 3rd.
You you left on March 2nd. Yeah.
So unfortunately I don't have the
Supreme Court document but I only have
news and news. I am not aware of any
such Supreme Court
directive. I'm not aware of it.
Okay. Then the other case you said once
you landed here your passport was
revoked. Mhm. You wanted to maybe come
back but you were yourself in shock that
the passport was revoked. Right. Yes.
Tell walk me through the day when you
got to know that you can't come back to
India.
I don't remember the exact date but I
like what were you going through when
did you get like the moment you got to
know that your passport been suspended
or revoked yeah but suspension
and other forms of restriction would
have been
um well understood or perceived
differently but revocation of a
passport it's the most severe form of
withdrawal
Right. To revoke. Yeah. So because I did
not attend the summons of the
enforcement
directors to which I replied and I said
I'm coming back but I need some time. I
need to arrange some money to pay off
the bank loans etc. Mhm. But they
revoked the passport.
what
they intended to achieve by revocation
of my passport. I still do not know. But
so on March 2nd you left. March 8th
banks informed Supreme Courts that you
have left the country.
On 15th April your suspension came for
your passport. Mhm. revocation the
suspension was 15th April 2016 and 24th
April was the revocation you know the
dates better than me okay fine so from
15 to 24 MEA says that because there was
no reply from you they had to revoke it
why didn't you reply between after 15
when you got to know that your your
passport getting suspended
I replied to them I I don't remember but
they revoked the passport I mean that's
what matters because you were not
replying to them. That's what their
reply is. That's what they officially
told you. That's what they have said it
officially in public. I'm not aware of
that. I I didn't go talk to them. I'm
not I'm not I can only talk about what I
could find online on through newspapers.
So that's the only thing unfortunately I
could talk about. Sad thing in my case
is a lot of people concoct things but
it's fine. I mean ultimately the bottom
line is the passport was revoked. Yeah.
Yeah. So and then and remains revoked.
So didn't you fight back? What is there
for me to do to get the password? I have
to claim my rights under the
constitution of India that I have a
constitutional right to a passport etc.
Yeah. So fight like everyone else like
the way you would go back and be like
this is wrongfully done to me. So let me
get my passport back. I'll fight it. Uh
I'll come back to the country. I'll
abide by the law and I'll fight in the
courts.
In your view, how many fronts should
somebody open
up? How many battles should you open up
and engage
in? Just
everything
unlimited. I have enough and more to
do, right? And I want to focus my legal
battles. Remember
they are not only time
consuming reading volumes of legal
papers is no
fun and lawyer lawyer fees are
expensive.
So, one at a
time. But don't you
think it makes it worse for you because
you didn't come back to the country?
They tag you as fugitive, fraud, and all
of these are tags because you choose to
not come back to the country. If I have
a fair assurance of a fair
trial and a dignified existence in
India, you may be right but I don't.
Would you be willing to return to
country if you're assured fair time? If
I am assured, absolutely I will I will
think about it seriously. But you should
also be
aware
that there are other
people who the government of India is
targeting for extradition from the UK
back to India.
In whose
case they have
got judgment from the high court of
appeal that Indian detention conditions
are violative of article 3 of the
constitution of the ECR I'm sorry and
therefore they can't be sent back.
The plea was
basically the prolonged detention
without trial for which we all know
there are numerous
examples. They just lock you up and
throw away the key. That's not justice.
But you were here extradicted as well,
right? You lost the case. It's all
right. I mean, I have illegal. They
arrested you as well and then they left.
They they granted you bail, right? What
happened? Normal part of extradition
normal that's the procedure what
happened with the extradition I think my
stay in England is fully legitimate
but you lost the case in UK high court
right to the Indian authorities there is
more than the particular case that you
are referring to so there are
proceedings ongoing
proceedings in this
country that's one of the legal battles
I'm
fighting that I told you about. But if
you're assured a fair trial, what do you
think is that assurance? What does it
look like? What guarantees would you
need that you would ever think of
considering? That's something for the
lawyers to discuss.
But if you would agree with me, the
conduct and the track record of the CBI
and ED in respect of other unfortunate
people doesn't inspire too much
confidence, does it?
I mean, I can rattle off a whole bunch
of names of
people, right? See let's talk about I
also tell you about the fact that in
India sadly a business
failure is compared or is is equivalent
to a fraud. But there are numerous cases
of Indian businessmen who have defaulted
on loan and they have still stayed in
the country and have fought and they
have not left the country and that's why
people don't call them ch they look them
in a bad eye because that's something
which socially we are conditioned to
look at in that way but they stayed
there that's why they've not been called
fugitives or chore okay and there are
cases like there's so many cases like
that fine call me a fugitive for not
going to India post
March. I didn't run away. I flew out of
India on a pre-cheduled visit. Right.
Fair enough. I did not return
for reasons that I consider are
valid. So if you want to call me a
fugitive, go ahead. But where's the
chore coming from? Where is the chi?
Because the agencies in the country,
CBI, ED, all the courts, the highest
court, they all have found
misrepresentation of funds and they have
cases against you and they've concluded
their cases by saying that your
financial transactions were not clean.
There's no chy
there. You took loan. your company,
Kingfisher Airlines, took a loan to
revive the company, but then you you
took that money and offshored that money
into different accounts around the
world. That's what the case is
about. If I'm not mistaken, I think CBI
in 2017, they concluded around 423
crores were found. Then ED said
something around 3,000 cr had some
problem with money laundering. So there
were these these numbers I can find
exact numbers and I can quote which I
found out. No problem. But why like EDS
said
3,547 cr was laundered in 2017. CBI
alleged that 423 cr was from Kingfisher
Airlines loan was siphoned off for
unrelated expenses. Can you explain why
that happened? Why these all these
agencies are against you and multiple
courts are against you and forget this
if you're calling India and everybody is
a system it's a nexist they all are
trying to make you a fraud multiple
international
courts Swiss Switzerland authorities UK
high court one of the courts from UK
they also found you guilty for
misrepresentation of funds right and
they've lost cases Swiss not co Swiss
authorities what what about the Swiss
authority they've also found that there
were transactions
authority have found
nothing. The Swiss authority froze my
children's accounts based on a request
by the government of
India. They did not adjudicate on
anything. The government of India wrote
to all these foreign governments saying
Vijay Malia and his family's property
should be frozen. Right? Only the Swiss
acted on it.
The French acted on it.
Fine. They were not stolen properties or
acquired from any money due to uh due
from Kingfisher Airlines to the banks.
There is absolutely no evidence. The CBI
and ED are well known to concoct,
fabricate and present false
evidence. That's fine. But they have to
prove it. As I said, the norm is you are
guil you are innocent until you are
proven guilty, not the other way around.
Now, let me explain the 423
crores. In an airline, more than
50% of operating costs are in foreign
currency. You lease planes, you pay in
dollars. Okay? You import spares, you
pay in dollars.
You have aircraft checks and services
you pay in
dollars,
right? So the money has to go out of
India. You can concoct whatever you want
and say that money sent out of India
means siphoning money. But why are they
calling unrelated expenses? If all of
these were the expenses for these
reasons, they would be related expenses.
But that is a question that the CBI must
answer. The allegations are against me.
I am refuting those
allegations. I am saying all these
allegations are complete nonsense. And
how would you explain 3,547 crores which
ED has alleged that's not sent out of
India. That is the borrowing from the
banks.
But they claim it has been laundered.
What is launder? If if I laundered it
means what are you suggesting? I stole
it. What is laundered? Laundered to me
is trying to turn cash to check and
check to cash. That's laundering.
Right? If they say I've laundered the
money, what are they saying I did with
that money? Did I steal
it? Did I fund my lifestyle with it?
What is the essence? What is the charge
of laundering? Here's the basic case.
Let me try to explain you what a common
man in India understands about your case
in very basics
language. If I borrow 100 rupees from a
bank, I use 50 rupees from that money to
buy a property outside India and I only
have 50 left and that 50 I spent in my
business trying to make it work. And
then when the banks are asking me to get
the money, I say I don't have any money.
Mhm. Now banks are not saying that why
did you burn the 50 rupees in making the
business work. They are questioning why
did you transfer this 50 rupees to buy
something else outside. So that is the
whole case and in your case numbers are
outrageous. So where is any iota of
evidence that I used even one rupee of
kingfisher airlines funds to acquire
overseas
properties? There is no such allegation.
So what are CBI and ED concluding then
what they have won cases in India.
They've concluded certain things and
that's why they're fighting on some
grounds. Why would UK courts even
entertain if there's no proof? Why would
anybody okay entertain what
Indian CBI
authorities action against you or case
against you if there's no proof? The job
of the UK court is only to establish and
determine whether there is a primma facy
case to be sent to
trial.
Right. The UK court has not adjudicated
and said you are either guilty or
innocent. The job of a UK extradition
judge is to say is what CBI is saying
fine is there a case to be tried in
front of a judge. That's the limit. They
have determined that. Now it is for the
CBI and me to fight it out. Okay. In the
court they provide their evidence. I
will provide my evidence. Okay. So
that's as far as the UK court is
concerned. Got it. So it has just got
gone to the trial. So absolutely. Okay.
What is the allegation?
I
misrepresented the Kingfisher
financials. Yeah. Right. To the IDBI.
Yeah. I colluded with the senior
management of the IDI to get the
loan. Right. And then I misuse the
proceeds of that 900 cr
loan. That is the three
allegations. The
allegation sub allegation about Formula
1 team
sponsorship. I responded to you earlier.
The Formula 1 team sent
back 10 million pounds to King Fisher
Airlines to help it. All
right. They brought in Royal Challengers
Bangalore as a cricket team. That was a
sponsorship
money
paid right for the umpire's
uniform where it said Fly King Fisher.
It was a pure for advertising. Of
course, the CBI says it was misuse of
funds. Fair enough. Everybody's entitled
to their opinion. But when the case is
tried before a judge, it is the judge
who will decide who is right, who wrong,
whether this tantamounts to siphoning or
diversion or improper
use in terms of the
collusion, right? There is not an iota
of proof. Not an iota of proof.
I met chairman Agarwal
twice and in two meetings along with
four other executive directors of IDBI
bank. Is it at all
conceivable that I would be able to make
some sort of corrupt backhanded
arrangement with them? Absolutely not.
But the loan was subsequently approved
by the IDBI board.
if there was something so blatantly
wrong in the sanction process because
King Fisher didn't meet the norms,
right? Kingfisher's financials were
weak. Yes, I agree. But the the board of
the IDBI bank would have would have
found out and commented upon it
themselves. They approved it
because the CB so the CBI are making
allegations all of which are fine. But
there is an equally robust defense
against these allegations. In the same
case when it comes to IDBI and all the
or the consortium of banks which gave
you loan
it is also said that there was an
independent agency from UK
which put out a brand valuation of 4,100
crores. Mhm. on Kingfisher's
brand but in reality the brand value was
only 160 crores when later was audited
by an independent valuer and that was
the mismanagement and that was the
collusion
between you and the IDPI board and
stuff that you sold them and you
misrepresented the brand value which in
reality was not the case.
Okay. So let me tell you there was no UK
independent agency. Grand thon Grand
Thornton is a very very wellestablished
accounting company hired by
me not by anybody else and the other
company was brand
finance. Both these companies gave a
brand
valuation right. I submitted the Grand
Thon brand valuation
report.
Right. The bank took
it. I had
two recognized
valuers submitted
one report which they accepted.
Now is that fraud on my part? If they
didn't want it, they said, "This is not
worth the paper it's written on, tear it
up and throw it away." I would have done
so. It's all very well in hindsight to
construct a case with all sorts of
frivolous
allegations
and if it's got to be in a court of law,
thrashed out, it will be. But how is
Supreme Court favoring all of these
then? Because none of my cases in the
Supreme Court. Supreme Court ordered you
to disclose all your assets on 21st
April 2016. Right. July. And they also
asked you
to pay bank a substantial amount to show
your commitment that you're ready to pay
everything because you kept saying that
you were ready to pay. Mhm. Right. Did
you do that? I made all the disclosures
under oath on behalf of myself and my
entire family including my
children. Now what's the case now? Where
is this heading in your words? Explain
me. Okay, forget all of these things.
We'll come back to what happened on 25th
February which you are recently which
recently you did filing a petition to
Karnataka court. Yeah. So let them gives
the statement of account. Yeah. So we
will come to the least. But in your
words, in simple words, summarize me,
give me a summary of series of events.
What exactly happened and why are you in
trouble? If I could just ask you to do
it in like next 4 5
minutes. You left the country. You
didn't intend to leave the country. You
were just you just left because there
was a pres-scheduled meeting. Then after
a month you get to know that you have
been suspended. Your passport has been
suspended. 8 n days later it gets
revoked and since then you're stuck
here. Mhm. In middle of it you get the
extradition process gets started. Two
times you get arrested but you grant you
have been granted
bail. The case gets to trial. Now CBI,
ED, the government in India, everybody
finds you guilty people. Nobody found me
guilty. I mean that's what they they're
calling it, right? They're giving you
names. Okay. Everybody has given you a
tag of let's just not use the word
guilty.
CBI hasn't taken place of guilt doesn't
arise. Yeah. So CBI, ED, multiple
courts, the government, people of India,
everybody calls you a fugitive, fraud,
chore. Mhm. bunch of different things,
anchors, news, media, everybody calls
you that, right? And you have been
publicly publicly on through your
Twitter on multiple occasions. You have
been saying that hey, I want to pay the
money. I want to pay the money. I really
want banks to listen to me. And you have
been very clear about it. There have
been multiple attempts from your side.
And again and again authorities
commenting
that though there has been an attempt
from your side but the
effectiveness of it needs to be
questioned. The seriousness of it needs
to be questioned. Right? This is what
the case is. But in all in all in
summary people call you chore. People
call you fugitive. People call you
fraud. Now explain me in summary what is
your side of story.
We've gone through the whole thing but I
want to understand just in short brief
the way I explained what is what is the
root cause for all this
money there is no other criminal
allegation against me it's all about
money
right I showed you the debt recovery
certificate amount 6203
crores I've shown you the ministry of
finance report 14,000 100
recovered. The question to be determined
now is has the money been recovered or
not? Once the
money has been fully recovered including
interest,
right? The root cause is taken care of.
No, the root cause is intention.
Sorry, the root cause is intention. Root
cause is not money and recovery of the
money. It started like that. The root
cause of your case is intention. You had
the money and you still didn't pay. That
is what we're fighting. That is what
everybody thinks that you that's why if
I answer the question, what was the
share values then and what are they at
the time of recovery? You'll get your
answer. The share value went up
tremendously. Therefore, they could
recover two and a half times the debt.
Back in 2016, the values of all the
securities were barely would cover the
debt recovery
certificates. So there was a huge
appreciation in the value of my shares
held. So it's fine. The root cause and
cause or lost to public to the common
man Indian
taxpayer is the money which has
been more than recovered. Right? Fine.
I'm ready to face trial for
intention. So if they want to convict me
for bad
intention, I'll fight it. Win or lose,
I'll fight it.
But you have a problem
with they calling you chore because
you've repaid the money. Yeah, I'm
probably the only chore who is being
called chore after repaying two and a
half times. But it's okay. I mean it's
part of life. You also filed a petition
in Karnataka High Court, right? What's
happening there? I don't know. That
petition as I told you was simply to
direct the blank banks to provide a
statement of account which once again I
find exceptionally strange. I mean this
probably the only example globally where
banks do not render a statement of
account. But if you say that you've
recovered everything and if bank provide
you the statement would you be open for
an independent audit? Of course, anytime
I'm open for it now on all your
financial transactions. No problem.
There's nothing to be hide. Zero.
Nothing. Please, anybody can help me.
Nothing.
Then if according to you the case is
this clean okay and the authorities are
questioning it the media is questioning
it. Do you think you flying out of India
just made your case worse? Maybe it did
but I flew out on a pre-arranged
commitment with no
uh court directive as you seem to
suggest that I must be
there. it. I
went to Geneva for a
meeting and
then you know the media fur that broke
out and the
environment was too
hot and too hostile and certainly not
conducive for an immediate return.
Plus, I needed to sell some
securities to overseas business partners
in order to generate more money to pay
these banks, which I've been trying to
sort of repay since 2016. Maybe not in
the quantum that finally has
resulted. I
mean, the banks have got lucky, isn't
it? Getting 4,100 crores because of the
appreciation of my shares.
14,000.
If I don't want to say I don't want to
comment on others. I might as well just
focus on my own
business. It's not fair. I'm not the
type of person who comments about other
people.
Do you think people would have still
calling you like people would still call
you fraud if
I have done whatever I could do? If you
would have stayed in India and
cooperated with banks,
sir, people would not call you for fine.
So people are abusing
me. Maybe we'll continue to abuse me.
There's nothing I can do about
it. That's why I kept quiet for 9 years.
Is there any proof where you requested
banks that I want to settle way before
all of this started? Of course, there is
proof. Can you give me? Sure. It's part
of Supreme Court record. How do we
access it? I ask my lawyers to give you
a copy. No problem at all. Easily done.
Before 2016.
Yes. Absolutely.
How do you want to be remembered? How do
you want Vijay Malia to be remembered?
For hopefully
for the good things that I might have
done. Certainly not
for being a jaw.
Perfect. All right. Okay. Thank you for
doing this. You're welcome.
Thank you so much for walking us through
every little detail of your case, your
life, and what's going on.
I just hope
that whichever party is right wins and
people see it the way you want to
deliver it and people see through every
little
thing
which they must have fed in a bad way or
wrong way. I don't know which side they
will believe. I don't know which side
media will believe. I don't know which
side the authorities will believe in,
but I hope they do the right thing. So,
thank you so much for walking us through
every little thing. Good. Thanks for
being here. Thank you.
Thank you so much for watching this
episode till the end. I take these kind
of episodes with utmost responsibility.
I'll see you the next time. Until then,
keep figuring out.
[Music]